<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-27T22:20:17+00:00</updated><id>https://alex-stephens.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alex Stephens</title><subtitle>Alex Stephens</subtitle><author><name>Alex Stephens</name><email>alex.stephens@eng.ox.ac.uk</email></author><entry><title type="html">`Shift + &amp;gt;` and the Importance of Making It Easy</title><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/make-it-easy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="`Shift + &amp;gt;` and the Importance of Making It Easy" /><published>2020-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/make-it-easy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/make-it-easy/">&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you picked up a new skill or habit that immediately became part of your natural way of doing things?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it was a couple of months ago, when I learned the keyboard shortcut &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;shift + &amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; (or simply &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;) on YouTube, which increases the speed of the current video by one increment (first to 1.25x, then 1.5x, 1.75x, and 2x). Dead easy, and yet this discovery has added a disproportionately huge amount of value to my daily life in the time since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;life-in-the-slow-lane&quot;&gt;Life in the slow lane&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a big fan of listening to podcasts sped up for quite a while now, since most podcast apps make this easy to do, and it allows me to get through more episodes than I otherwise could. I find that speeding things up a bit actually makes them more engaging and enjoyable to listen to, although the exact speed I opt for depends on the particular podcast. For more information-dense ones, I may find 1x or 1.25x is a comfortable pace, whereas others I can comfortably listen to at 1.75x or 2x. It also depends a bit on what I’m up to while listening - if I’m out on a run, my attention will be almost entirely on the podcast, so I can listen at higher speeds, whereas if I’m cooking or driving my attention might be divided so I’ll opt for slightly slower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consume plenty of content on YouTube, be it educational, entertainment, or a combination of the two, but until recently I have never regularly adjusted the playback speed on there. The main reason for this is that the user interface makes it pretty cumbersome, requiring three clicks through the menu to change speed once (and then another two if you immediately realise you want to change it again). My preferred playback speed for a given video could be anywhere from 1.25x to 2x, but the effort to adjust it for every video I watched was too much, so I never did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as I learned the shortcuts (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;shift + &amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to increase speed by one increment, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;shift + &amp;lt;&lt;/code&gt; to slow down), it changed the game almost immediately. Suddenly, it was almost no effort to jump between different speeds and find the fastest comfortable one. No need to distract myself from the video by having to click through the menus - in fact, no need to even glance away from the video while fiddling with the speed. Since discovering this shortcut, I adjust the playback speed on virtually every video I watch, more or less without thinking, and the improvement to my overall YouTube experience has been huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;make-it-easy&quot;&gt;Make it easy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever ventured into the world of self-help and productivity literature, you’ve probably heard of &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamesclear.com/atomic-habits&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt; by James Clear, which if you aren’t familiar, is a great practical guide on how habits are built and maintained. In this book, Clear describes what he calls the Four Laws of Behaviour Change, the third of which is “Make It Easy”. It is human nature to prefer actions that require less effort, so by making a habit easier to do, you become more likely to follow through with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimising my playback speed for videos was something that, on some level, I have wanted to do for a long time. However, that tiny extra effort of three clicks through a menu was enough to deter me from ever actually doing it. As soon as it became a single two-button keyboard shortcut, it became a habit that I am virtually guaranteed to continue with for the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So take the a couple of minutes to flick through the keyboard shortcuts for programs (or, in this case, websites) that you spend a lot of time on, and try some of them out. Most of them probably won’t stick, but those few that you do end up using constantly are the ones that make all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Stephens</name><email>alex.stephens@eng.ox.ac.uk</email></author><summary type="html">When was the last time you picked up a new skill or habit that immediately became part of your natural way of doing things? For me, it was a couple of months ago, when I learned the keyboard shortcut shift + &amp;gt; (or simply &amp;gt;) on YouTube, which increases the speed of the current video by one increment (first to 1.25x, then 1.5x, 1.75x, and 2x). Dead easy, and yet this discovery has added a disproportionately huge amount of value to my daily life in the time since. Life in the slow lane I’ve been a big fan of listening to podcasts sped up for quite a while now, since most podcast apps make this easy to do, and it allows me to get through more episodes than I otherwise could. I find that speeding things up a bit actually makes them more engaging and enjoyable to listen to, although the exact speed I opt for depends on the particular podcast. For more information-dense ones, I may find 1x or 1.25x is a comfortable pace, whereas others I can comfortably listen to at 1.75x or 2x. It also depends a bit on what I’m up to while listening - if I’m out on a run, my attention will be almost entirely on the podcast, so I can listen at higher speeds, whereas if I’m cooking or driving my attention might be divided so I’ll opt for slightly slower. I consume plenty of content on YouTube, be it educational, entertainment, or a combination of the two, but until recently I have never regularly adjusted the playback speed on there. The main reason for this is that the user interface makes it pretty cumbersome, requiring three clicks through the menu to change speed once (and then another two if you immediately realise you want to change it again). My preferred playback speed for a given video could be anywhere from 1.25x to 2x, but the effort to adjust it for every video I watched was too much, so I never did it. As soon as I learned the shortcuts (shift + &amp;gt; to increase speed by one increment, shift + &amp;lt; to slow down), it changed the game almost immediately. Suddenly, it was almost no effort to jump between different speeds and find the fastest comfortable one. No need to distract myself from the video by having to click through the menus - in fact, no need to even glance away from the video while fiddling with the speed. Since discovering this shortcut, I adjust the playback speed on virtually every video I watch, more or less without thinking, and the improvement to my overall YouTube experience has been huge. Make it easy If you’ve ever ventured into the world of self-help and productivity literature, you’ve probably heard of Atomic Habits by James Clear, which if you aren’t familiar, is a great practical guide on how habits are built and maintained. In this book, Clear describes what he calls the Four Laws of Behaviour Change, the third of which is “Make It Easy”. It is human nature to prefer actions that require less effort, so by making a habit easier to do, you become more likely to follow through with it. Optimising my playback speed for videos was something that, on some level, I have wanted to do for a long time. However, that tiny extra effort of three clicks through a menu was enough to deter me from ever actually doing it. As soon as it became a single two-button keyboard shortcut, it became a habit that I am virtually guaranteed to continue with for the foreseeable future. So take the a couple of minutes to flick through the keyboard shortcuts for programs (or, in this case, websites) that you spend a lot of time on, and try some of them out. Most of them probably won’t stick, but those few that you do end up using constantly are the ones that make all the difference.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Rule of Six</title><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/rule-of-six/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rule of Six" /><published>2020-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/rule-of-six</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/rule-of-six/">&lt;p&gt;About a month ago, I moved from Australia to the UK to start a PhD at the University of Oxford. While I was quite excited for the move despite the uncertainty of relocating halfway around the world during a global pandemic, I still arrived with the expectation that I would not be able to have the usual social experience of a new student (a &lt;em&gt;fresher&lt;/em&gt;, if you will) at Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the hallmarks of this experience is Freshers’ Week, the week before the academic year starts, during which the colleges (one of which every student at Oxford is a member of) run the gamut of social events that you might expect for a bunch of uni students who want to make new friends - which is to say, a lot of drinking events, and a couple of other events that will probably end up involving alcohol at some point too. In my case, the events were organised by the graduate student committee of Exeter College, catering to the 100 or so graduate students joining the college for the 2020-21 academic year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-rule-of-six&quot;&gt;The rule of six&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, all of these events had to be organised in accordance with the UK Government health guidelines, most notably the  dramatically named “rule of six”. As the name implies, this rule restricts all social gatherings to a maximum of six people in any setting - indoors, outdoors, public venues, private accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rule of six meant that the Freshers’ Week events this year looked quite different than usual. Where there might previously have been rowdy parties, pub nights, or big outdoor evemts, we now faced a series of events that were all carefully planned to comply with guidelines. Pre-registration became essential, and any events at pubs or restaurants were limited to bookings of 6 with strictly communication between tables. Some events were designed around “household” groups, the small groups of students sharing living spaces at the college accommodation complex, who were considered to form a social bubble within which COVID transmission was an accepted risk. The result was that all of the events essentially involved hanging out with the same small group of people for an entire afternoon or evening, with no mixing whatsoever with other groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, the point of this post is not to complain about any of this - in fact quite the opposite. These rules are obviously important, and the Exeter fresher cohort was extremely grateful that the committee went to the considerable effort of planning out all of these events for us under the challenging circumstances. The freshers at some of the other Oxford colleges weren’t so lucky, and essentially missed out on the Freshers’ Week social experience altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually came out of Freshers’ Week feeling that I’d made plenty of friends and generally had an excellent time at all of the events, despite some misgivings from before it all got started. However, this was initially tinged with the understanding that it could have been &lt;em&gt;even better&lt;/em&gt; in the absence of the pandemic, and that we’d somehow missed out on the “full experience”… But the more I thought about it in the days after, the more I realised that actually although some of the events might not have been as superficially exciting this year, they were actually a &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; experience for connecting with new people and making friends, which is exactly the point of Freshers’ Week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-optionality&quot;&gt;Social optionality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand how I came to the conclusion that the rule of six restriction improved my experience of Freshers’ Week, let’s take a quick look at the idea of &lt;em&gt;social optionality&lt;/em&gt;. I came across this concept in an episode of the podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://notoverthinking.com/&quot;&gt;Not Overthinking&lt;/a&gt;, in which one of the hosts, Taimur Abdaal, introduces the idea as a way of thinking about how we approach social interactions. He has a great blog post about it which you can check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://taimur.me/posts/against-social-optionality/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if you’re interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The social optionality of an event or situation refers to how easy it is to engage or disengage with social interactions. An example of a high social optionality situation might be a networking event or a large party, where everyone is meeting new people, and it’s generally pretty easy to eject yourself from a conversation and move onto another one if you don’t feel like you’re hitting it off with someone. At the other end of the scale, an example Taimur uses of a low optionality event is a group holiday, where a group of, say, 8 people go somewhere for a couple of days, and are basically committed to engaging socially with each other for this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key ideas that Taimur presents about this is that the social optionality of a situation significantly changes how we approach it. In a very high optionality scenario, we are constantly - either consciously or subconsciously - evaluating new people we interact with - we are thinking, am I getting along with this person? Is this the kind of person I want to become better friends with? If we’re not convinced, it’s easy to just move on and find someone else to talk to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In low optionality events, this mindset doesn’t work any more - we know that we &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to interact with the people around us, so we instead start thinking about &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to connect with them. We throw away our superficial judgements, and look for common ground upon which to build a connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Wanting to connect for no other reason than because you’re two human beings on the same floating rock — this is the intention with which I’d like to approach all social interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taimur concludes that the high optionality mindset causes us to miss out on making meaningful connections because we more ready to dismiss people instead of putting in the effort, and that ideally we should approach all interactions with something akin to the low optionality mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-unexpected-result&quot;&gt;The unexpected result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusion I came to is that the effect of the UK Government’s social gathering restrictions on Freshers’ Week experience at Exeter College was precisely to &lt;em&gt;lower the social optionality of all of the events&lt;/em&gt;. Had Freshers’ Week involved, for example, the big wine and cheese night that is sometimes on the agenda, I have no doubt that I would have had a great time, and probably chatted with loads of new people in the space of a few short hours. However, it’s likely that many of these conversations would have been that typical awkward small talk that sometimes dominates events where nobody knows each other, and I probably would’ve forgotten the names of many of the people I met by the following morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, at pretty much all events I attended, I spoke for at least couple of hours with the same four or five people. While this might seem superficially less exciting than the wine and cheese night, I found that the conversations I did have were far better than what I would typically expect from talking to a group of people I’d just met and didn’t necessarily have much in common with besides the university we attend. By the end of Freshers’ Week, I found that I had a whole lot of small groups of new friends from these events, each of which will now happily continue to meet up (in a socially responsible manner, of course), often with someone bringing along a new person or two to introduce to the rest if capacity allows. Since &lt;em&gt;every event&lt;/em&gt; involved only a few people, I felt that I was able to connect better with new people, have more interesting conversations, and become closer than would otherwise have been possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, strange as it might seem, for this one week that kicked off my new life as a PhD student in a foreign country, the government restrictions on social gatherings actually &lt;em&gt;improved&lt;/em&gt; my social experience significantly. The social events, adapting to the challenging circumstances, turned into lower optionality settings which - although perhaps superficially less exciting at times - were genuinely more valuable because of it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Stephens</name><email>alex.stephens@eng.ox.ac.uk</email></author><summary type="html">About a month ago, I moved from Australia to the UK to start a PhD at the University of Oxford. While I was quite excited for the move despite the uncertainty of relocating halfway around the world during a global pandemic, I still arrived with the expectation that I would not be able to have the usual social experience of a new student (a fresher, if you will) at Oxford. One of the hallmarks of this experience is Freshers’ Week, the week before the academic year starts, during which the colleges (one of which every student at Oxford is a member of) run the gamut of social events that you might expect for a bunch of uni students who want to make new friends - which is to say, a lot of drinking events, and a couple of other events that will probably end up involving alcohol at some point too. In my case, the events were organised by the graduate student committee of Exeter College, catering to the 100 or so graduate students joining the college for the 2020-21 academic year. The rule of six This year, all of these events had to be organised in accordance with the UK Government health guidelines, most notably the dramatically named “rule of six”. As the name implies, this rule restricts all social gatherings to a maximum of six people in any setting - indoors, outdoors, public venues, private accommodation. The rule of six meant that the Freshers’ Week events this year looked quite different than usual. Where there might previously have been rowdy parties, pub nights, or big outdoor evemts, we now faced a series of events that were all carefully planned to comply with guidelines. Pre-registration became essential, and any events at pubs or restaurants were limited to bookings of 6 with strictly communication between tables. Some events were designed around “household” groups, the small groups of students sharing living spaces at the college accommodation complex, who were considered to form a social bubble within which COVID transmission was an accepted risk. The result was that all of the events essentially involved hanging out with the same small group of people for an entire afternoon or evening, with no mixing whatsoever with other groups. Don’t get me wrong, the point of this post is not to complain about any of this - in fact quite the opposite. These rules are obviously important, and the Exeter fresher cohort was extremely grateful that the committee went to the considerable effort of planning out all of these events for us under the challenging circumstances. The freshers at some of the other Oxford colleges weren’t so lucky, and essentially missed out on the Freshers’ Week social experience altogether. I actually came out of Freshers’ Week feeling that I’d made plenty of friends and generally had an excellent time at all of the events, despite some misgivings from before it all got started. However, this was initially tinged with the understanding that it could have been even better in the absence of the pandemic, and that we’d somehow missed out on the “full experience”… But the more I thought about it in the days after, the more I realised that actually although some of the events might not have been as superficially exciting this year, they were actually a better experience for connecting with new people and making friends, which is exactly the point of Freshers’ Week. Social optionality To understand how I came to the conclusion that the rule of six restriction improved my experience of Freshers’ Week, let’s take a quick look at the idea of social optionality. I came across this concept in an episode of the podcast Not Overthinking, in which one of the hosts, Taimur Abdaal, introduces the idea as a way of thinking about how we approach social interactions. He has a great blog post about it which you can check out here if you’re interested. The social optionality of an event or situation refers to how easy it is to engage or disengage with social interactions. An example of a high social optionality situation might be a networking event or a large party, where everyone is meeting new people, and it’s generally pretty easy to eject yourself from a conversation and move onto another one if you don’t feel like you’re hitting it off with someone. At the other end of the scale, an example Taimur uses of a low optionality event is a group holiday, where a group of, say, 8 people go somewhere for a couple of days, and are basically committed to engaging socially with each other for this time. One of the key ideas that Taimur presents about this is that the social optionality of a situation significantly changes how we approach it. In a very high optionality scenario, we are constantly - either consciously or subconsciously - evaluating new people we interact with - we are thinking, am I getting along with this person? Is this the kind of person I want to become better friends with? If we’re not convinced, it’s easy to just move on and find someone else to talk to. In low optionality events, this mindset doesn’t work any more - we know that we have to interact with the people around us, so we instead start thinking about how to connect with them. We throw away our superficial judgements, and look for common ground upon which to build a connection. Wanting to connect for no other reason than because you’re two human beings on the same floating rock — this is the intention with which I’d like to approach all social interactions. Taimur concludes that the high optionality mindset causes us to miss out on making meaningful connections because we more ready to dismiss people instead of putting in the effort, and that ideally we should approach all interactions with something akin to the low optionality mindset. The unexpected result The conclusion I came to is that the effect of the UK Government’s social gathering restrictions on Freshers’ Week experience at Exeter College was precisely to lower the social optionality of all of the events. Had Freshers’ Week involved, for example, the big wine and cheese night that is sometimes on the agenda, I have no doubt that I would have had a great time, and probably chatted with loads of new people in the space of a few short hours. However, it’s likely that many of these conversations would have been that typical awkward small talk that sometimes dominates events where nobody knows each other, and I probably would’ve forgotten the names of many of the people I met by the following morning. Instead, at pretty much all events I attended, I spoke for at least couple of hours with the same four or five people. While this might seem superficially less exciting than the wine and cheese night, I found that the conversations I did have were far better than what I would typically expect from talking to a group of people I’d just met and didn’t necessarily have much in common with besides the university we attend. By the end of Freshers’ Week, I found that I had a whole lot of small groups of new friends from these events, each of which will now happily continue to meet up (in a socially responsible manner, of course), often with someone bringing along a new person or two to introduce to the rest if capacity allows. Since every event involved only a few people, I felt that I was able to connect better with new people, have more interesting conversations, and become closer than would otherwise have been possible. So, strange as it might seem, for this one week that kicked off my new life as a PhD student in a foreign country, the government restrictions on social gatherings actually improved my social experience significantly. The social events, adapting to the challenging circumstances, turned into lower optionality settings which - although perhaps superficially less exciting at times - were genuinely more valuable because of it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Demon Haunted World of COVID-19</title><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/demon-haunted-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Demon Haunted World of COVID-19" /><published>2020-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/demon-haunted-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/demon-haunted-world/">&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, I came across a quote that has been circulating online a fair bit this year. The quote comes from the 1995 book &lt;em&gt;The Demon Haunted World&lt;/em&gt; by the American astrophysicist and science communicator Carl Sagan, and reads as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have a foreboding of an America in my children’s or grandchildren’s time – when the United States is a service and information economy; when nearly all the manufacturing industries have slipped away to other countries; when awesome technological powers are in the hands of a very few, and no one representing the public interest can even grasp the issues; when the people have lost the ability to set their own agendas or knowledgeably question those in authority; when, clutching our crystals and nervously consulting our horoscopes, our critical faculties in decline, unable to distinguish between what feels good and what’s true, we slide, almost without noticing, back into superstition and darkness…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This passage, particularly the final third, resonated quite strongly with me because I felt that despite having been published 25 years ago, it hints at some of the greatest issues facing our the pandemic-stricken world today. Throughout the COVID-19 pandemic this year, I have been surprised on many occasions by the number of people who have seemed willing to ideologically reject scientific advice. How is it that in 2020, when our collective scientific understanding is the most developed and accessible that it has ever been, that well-established science can still be reduced to a matter of opinion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June, Dr Anthony Fauci, one of top infectious disease experts and health advisors in the US, lamented the “anti-science bias” present in the country, attributing the country’s ineffective pandemic response to this bias. Be it refusal to wear face masks in public, or denial of the existence of the virus altogether, anti-scientific attitudes have run rampant this year. My first thought upon reading the above quote was that Sagan, who died in 1996, would not have been surprised by this. I wondered if the book might help me to better understand our collective response to the coronavirus pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;preferring-the-darkness&quot;&gt;Preferring the darkness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full title of Sagan’s book is &lt;em&gt;The Demon-Haunted World: Science as a Candle in the Dark&lt;/em&gt;. The subtitle is a reference to the 1656 book &lt;em&gt;A Candle in the Dark&lt;/em&gt; by Thomas Ady, a sceptical attack on the then-popular practice of witch-hunting. Witches were persecuted for their supposed supernatural abilities, used as scapegoats for various misfortunes, and frequently forced by torture to confess to various crimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ady describes the witch mania as a scam “to delude the people”, arguing against the interpretations of the Bible that were frequently used to justify witch-hunting. Quoting a justification given by witchmongers for the existence of witches, Ady writes, “witches must exist, else how should these things be, or come to pass?” The popular mindset in England during Ady’s time was strongly determined by religious leaders, and their conclusions were rarely questioned so directly. In an era in which people were fearful of the outside world, they turned readily to anywhere that would explain away their terrors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sagan draws parallels between the witch mania and the alien abduction phenomenon of the later 20th century. He points out that although the entire concept could be explained away by fairly basic lines of questioning, many people claimed nonetheless to have been abducted by aliens, and many more believed these stories. The common traits of the supposed aliens were particularly telling – in different cultures’ representations of them, they always bore strong resemblance to humans. People who claimed to have communicated with aliens would never learn any interesting information from them (new scientific knowledge or answers to unsolved mathematical problems, for example) only vague statements about the meaning of life that could easily have been conjured up by an attention seeker. Their warnings for the future always centred on well-known fears (e.g. that of nuclear war in the 1950s), never demonstrating any convincing foreknowledge. The concept of alien abduction did not hold up to basic scepticism, and yet people &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to believe in aliens, so they did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;additional-driving-forces&quot;&gt;Additional driving forces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of societal upheaval, the fact that we tend to prefer to hold onto our existing worldview is not particularly surprising. There is little to enjoy about any of the widespread behaviour changes demanded by COVID, and many have led to significant hardships for large portions of the population. In the US and many other countries, this tendency is compounded by the poor standard of scientific education, which contributes to a society in which people do not think critically about the information they are presented. As soon as an anti-scientific movement gains a little steam, it is readily adopted by the large cross-section of society who see it as a preferable alternative to accepting the reality of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I feel like these two key points – our natural preference for preserving existing worldviews, compounded by a lack of education in scepticism and critical thought – go a decent way towards explaining the anti-science bias present in much of the world today. However, I would say that there is a third element which is also an essential part of the picture, and that is the presence of &lt;em&gt;direct incentives to go against science,&lt;/em&gt; which exist at all levels of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The countries whose COVID-19 responses I have followed most closely are Australia – where I was living for the first few months of the pandemic – as well as the United States and several European countries, due largely to their prominence in media coverage. Many of these are strongly capitalistic societies, in which many motives that run counter to public health advice have been very clearly on display in the last few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sagan’s book discusses a couple of examples of similar phenomena in recent history – it is worth looking at one of these in a bit of depth to see some parallels with what is happening now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;smoke-and-mirrors&quot;&gt;Smoke and mirrors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1960s, it is estimated that over 40% of Americans were regular smokers, a number that plummeted in the subsequent decades. This was largely due to a variety of scientific studies conducted in the 1950s and 1960s that demonstrated causal links between smoking and a variety of adverse health effects. However, the attitude shift in the medical community was slow, and is thought to have been hindered by resistance from nicotine-dependent doctors who were reluctant to believe in the dangers of smoking. The tobacco industry used its considerable influence to suppress scientific studies and lobby against tobacco controls that came under consideration as a result of these studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sagan’s book references a 1971 internal report from the Brown and Williamson Tobacco Corporation, claiming that the industry was a victim of unsupported claims drawing false links to lung cancer and calling this the “greatest libel and slander ever perpetrated against any product in the history of free enterprise”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, this strikes a chord with what we see today - powerful, profit-driven entities digging their heels in to prevent the acceptance of ideas that will inevitably be financially damaging. Incentives to go against health advice are present at all levels in capitalist society, from the industrial CEO who wants to avoid a lockdown so that their factories can remain productive, to the working adult who cannot afford to two weeks of work for self-isolation even when they show symptoms of COVID. These sentiments are propagated through the media we consume, leaving people in a position where they can choose a narrative that suits them best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A point that is worth clarifying here is that these incentives only directly encourage us to &lt;em&gt;act&lt;/em&gt; against the scientific advice, not necessarily to actually disbelieve it  – a completely rational person could understand the dangers of the virus and yet go to work anyway because they need to earn money to support their family. Somewhat similarly, many people smoke cigarettes because they enjoy doing so, even if they understand the long-term health risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at a certain point, it becomes tempting to start to self-justify, and to actually &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; that what we are doing is unequivocally right – we would rather not think about the compromises we have made. This is expressed by Sagan as a trend seen throughout history:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the saddest lessons of history is this: if we’ve been bamboozled long enough, we tend to reject any evidence of the bamboozle. We’re no longer interested in finding out the truth. The bamboozle has captured us. It’s simply too painful to acknowledge, even to ourselves, that we’ve been taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This acts as a first step in disconnecting ourselves from reality, by choosing to believe something that we once knew on a rational level to be false. We must be willing to critically examine our own beliefs and the foundations upon which they are built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-path-forwards&quot;&gt;The path forwards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main idea that was driven home for me by Sagan’s book is that any society that is not well-educated in critical thought and scepticism is one that will readily slide into superstition and darkness. Our willingness to accept information that changes our view of the world competes with our natural resistance to change, a balance that can be tipped further against science by societal pressures. By actively examining our own beliefs, and questioning the assumptions and motives behind the information that is presented to us, perhaps we can work towards tipping the balance back the other way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Stephens</name><email>alex.stephens@eng.ox.ac.uk</email></author><summary type="html">A couple of months ago, I came across a quote that has been circulating online a fair bit this year. The quote comes from the 1995 book The Demon Haunted World by the American astrophysicist and science communicator Carl Sagan, and reads as follows: I have a foreboding of an America in my children’s or grandchildren’s time – when the United States is a service and information economy; when nearly all the manufacturing industries have slipped away to other countries; when awesome technological powers are in the hands of a very few, and no one representing the public interest can even grasp the issues; when the people have lost the ability to set their own agendas or knowledgeably question those in authority; when, clutching our crystals and nervously consulting our horoscopes, our critical faculties in decline, unable to distinguish between what feels good and what’s true, we slide, almost without noticing, back into superstition and darkness… This passage, particularly the final third, resonated quite strongly with me because I felt that despite having been published 25 years ago, it hints at some of the greatest issues facing our the pandemic-stricken world today. Throughout the COVID-19 pandemic this year, I have been surprised on many occasions by the number of people who have seemed willing to ideologically reject scientific advice. How is it that in 2020, when our collective scientific understanding is the most developed and accessible that it has ever been, that well-established science can still be reduced to a matter of opinion? In June, Dr Anthony Fauci, one of top infectious disease experts and health advisors in the US, lamented the “anti-science bias” present in the country, attributing the country’s ineffective pandemic response to this bias. Be it refusal to wear face masks in public, or denial of the existence of the virus altogether, anti-scientific attitudes have run rampant this year. My first thought upon reading the above quote was that Sagan, who died in 1996, would not have been surprised by this. I wondered if the book might help me to better understand our collective response to the coronavirus pandemic. Preferring the darkness The full title of Sagan’s book is The Demon-Haunted World: Science as a Candle in the Dark. The subtitle is a reference to the 1656 book A Candle in the Dark by Thomas Ady, a sceptical attack on the then-popular practice of witch-hunting. Witches were persecuted for their supposed supernatural abilities, used as scapegoats for various misfortunes, and frequently forced by torture to confess to various crimes. Ady describes the witch mania as a scam “to delude the people”, arguing against the interpretations of the Bible that were frequently used to justify witch-hunting. Quoting a justification given by witchmongers for the existence of witches, Ady writes, “witches must exist, else how should these things be, or come to pass?” The popular mindset in England during Ady’s time was strongly determined by religious leaders, and their conclusions were rarely questioned so directly. In an era in which people were fearful of the outside world, they turned readily to anywhere that would explain away their terrors. Sagan draws parallels between the witch mania and the alien abduction phenomenon of the later 20th century. He points out that although the entire concept could be explained away by fairly basic lines of questioning, many people claimed nonetheless to have been abducted by aliens, and many more believed these stories. The common traits of the supposed aliens were particularly telling – in different cultures’ representations of them, they always bore strong resemblance to humans. People who claimed to have communicated with aliens would never learn any interesting information from them (new scientific knowledge or answers to unsolved mathematical problems, for example) only vague statements about the meaning of life that could easily have been conjured up by an attention seeker. Their warnings for the future always centred on well-known fears (e.g. that of nuclear war in the 1950s), never demonstrating any convincing foreknowledge. The concept of alien abduction did not hold up to basic scepticism, and yet people wanted to believe in aliens, so they did. Additional driving forces In the face of societal upheaval, the fact that we tend to prefer to hold onto our existing worldview is not particularly surprising. There is little to enjoy about any of the widespread behaviour changes demanded by COVID, and many have led to significant hardships for large portions of the population. In the US and many other countries, this tendency is compounded by the poor standard of scientific education, which contributes to a society in which people do not think critically about the information they are presented. As soon as an anti-scientific movement gains a little steam, it is readily adopted by the large cross-section of society who see it as a preferable alternative to accepting the reality of the pandemic. At this point, I feel like these two key points – our natural preference for preserving existing worldviews, compounded by a lack of education in scepticism and critical thought – go a decent way towards explaining the anti-science bias present in much of the world today. However, I would say that there is a third element which is also an essential part of the picture, and that is the presence of direct incentives to go against science, which exist at all levels of society. The countries whose COVID-19 responses I have followed most closely are Australia – where I was living for the first few months of the pandemic – as well as the United States and several European countries, due largely to their prominence in media coverage. Many of these are strongly capitalistic societies, in which many motives that run counter to public health advice have been very clearly on display in the last few months. Sagan’s book discusses a couple of examples of similar phenomena in recent history – it is worth looking at one of these in a bit of depth to see some parallels with what is happening now. Smoke and mirrors In the 1960s, it is estimated that over 40% of Americans were regular smokers, a number that plummeted in the subsequent decades. This was largely due to a variety of scientific studies conducted in the 1950s and 1960s that demonstrated causal links between smoking and a variety of adverse health effects. However, the attitude shift in the medical community was slow, and is thought to have been hindered by resistance from nicotine-dependent doctors who were reluctant to believe in the dangers of smoking. The tobacco industry used its considerable influence to suppress scientific studies and lobby against tobacco controls that came under consideration as a result of these studies. Sagan’s book references a 1971 internal report from the Brown and Williamson Tobacco Corporation, claiming that the industry was a victim of unsupported claims drawing false links to lung cancer and calling this the “greatest libel and slander ever perpetrated against any product in the history of free enterprise”. To me, this strikes a chord with what we see today - powerful, profit-driven entities digging their heels in to prevent the acceptance of ideas that will inevitably be financially damaging. Incentives to go against health advice are present at all levels in capitalist society, from the industrial CEO who wants to avoid a lockdown so that their factories can remain productive, to the working adult who cannot afford to two weeks of work for self-isolation even when they show symptoms of COVID. These sentiments are propagated through the media we consume, leaving people in a position where they can choose a narrative that suits them best. A point that is worth clarifying here is that these incentives only directly encourage us to act against the scientific advice, not necessarily to actually disbelieve it – a completely rational person could understand the dangers of the virus and yet go to work anyway because they need to earn money to support their family. Somewhat similarly, many people smoke cigarettes because they enjoy doing so, even if they understand the long-term health risks. However, at a certain point, it becomes tempting to start to self-justify, and to actually believe that what we are doing is unequivocally right – we would rather not think about the compromises we have made. This is expressed by Sagan as a trend seen throughout history: One of the saddest lessons of history is this: if we’ve been bamboozled long enough, we tend to reject any evidence of the bamboozle. We’re no longer interested in finding out the truth. The bamboozle has captured us. It’s simply too painful to acknowledge, even to ourselves, that we’ve been taken. This acts as a first step in disconnecting ourselves from reality, by choosing to believe something that we once knew on a rational level to be false. We must be willing to critically examine our own beliefs and the foundations upon which they are built. The path forwards The main idea that was driven home for me by Sagan’s book is that any society that is not well-educated in critical thought and scepticism is one that will readily slide into superstition and darkness. Our willingness to accept information that changes our view of the world competes with our natural resistance to change, a balance that can be tipped further against science by societal pressures. By actively examining our own beliefs, and questioning the assumptions and motives behind the information that is presented to us, perhaps we can work towards tipping the balance back the other way.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Generative Art: Greater than the Sum of its Parts</title><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/generative/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Generative Art: Greater than the Sum of its Parts" /><published>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/generative</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/generative/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-generative-art&quot;&gt;What is generative art?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Generative art refers to any art practice where the artist uses a system, such
as a set of natural language rules, a computer program, a machine, or other
procedural invention, which is set into motion with some degree of autonomy
contributing to or resulting in a completed work of art.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.90.2634&quot;&gt;Philip Galanter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since first learning of the concept of generative art, I have been intrigued by what it has to offer. The idea of creating art with computer programs in particular caught my interest, since this is a medium that is both familiar and accessible to me. Experimenting with it myself, with the help of a variety of online resources, revealed the rich possibilities of creating visually satisfying artworks from foundations of algorithms and mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of generating art programmatically typically involves randomness and tuneable parameters, making it highly dynamic and iterative. As I experimented I found I was often surprised by the results that came from changing parameters in my code, leading me to ideas that were not part of my original vision. Equally fun is looking at other peoples’ generated artworks, and trying to deduce what algorithms or mathematical concepts might have been used to create them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of resources online that explain in more detail what generative art really is, and the many different tools and techniques that are used to create it, so these aspects won’t be the focus here (although if you are interested in a broader introduction to generative art, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artnome.com/news/2018/8/8/why-love-generative-art&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; is excellent). The aim of this post is to demonstrate how an extremely simple base element or idea can be iterated upon to generate patterns that are (in my opinion, at least) surprisingly complex and pleasing to the eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;generating-a-simple-pattern&quot;&gt;Generating a simple pattern&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start off, let’s have a look at an example of a generative art pattern, which I created using the Javascript library &lt;a href=&quot;https://p5js.org/&quot;&gt;p5.js&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/basic.png&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks pretty nice, right? Take a minute to look carefully at the image above, and think about this key question - &lt;strong&gt;how would you recreate the pattern?&lt;/strong&gt; We want to come up with a &lt;em&gt;plain English description&lt;/em&gt; of how one could go about producing something that looks like this. Can you come up with a simple process that would achieve this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is probably a lot simpler than you’re thinking - the solutions that I went to at first were definitely unnecessarily complex. In fact, all you need to construct the pattern is the two tiles shown below, each consisting of a pair of opposing quarter circles. They’re really the same tile, just with a 90 degree rotational offset between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/tile-1.png&quot; width=&quot;25%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/tile-2.png&quot; width=&quot;25%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make this a bit clearer, here’s the original pattern again, this time with the tiles outlined:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/basic-outline.png&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first saw this, which is an example of something called a &lt;em&gt;Truchet pattern&lt;/em&gt;, I was pretty amazed by how simple it was to create. I was intrigued by the fact that it was not obvious from looking at the pattern how one would go about reproducing it, and yet once I found out the solution it was suddenly so simple. This, I think, is important in many types of generative art - the underlying ideas are often not as complex as they might seem at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;developing-the-pattern&quot;&gt;Developing the pattern&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what else can we do with this type of pattern? One way to extend the design is by layering the pattern at multiple scales, using different shades and line thicknesses to create aesthetic variation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;carouselTruchetBW&quot; class=&quot;carousel slide carousel-fade&quot; data-ride=&quot;carousel&quot; data-interval=&quot;1500&quot;&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-inner&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-item active&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/bw-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Base pattern&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-item&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/bw-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Second layer&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-item&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/bw-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Third layer&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;a class=&quot;carousel-control-prev&quot; href=&quot;#carouselTruchetBW&quot; role=&quot;button&quot; data-slide=&quot;prev&quot;&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;carousel-control-prev-icon&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;sr-only&quot;&gt;Previous&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;a class=&quot;carousel-control-next&quot; href=&quot;#carouselTruchetBW&quot; role=&quot;button&quot; data-slide=&quot;next&quot;&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;carousel-control-next-icon&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;sr-only&quot;&gt;Next&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the beauty of generating art from code is that once the base program is written, modifications of this type (scaling, layering, etc.) are quick and easy. This is part of why the genre lends itself so well to experimentation, either manually or through randomisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, let’s add some colour. Shown below are a few more layered Truchet patterns, created with somewhat randomised sizes and scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;carouselTruchetColored&quot; class=&quot;carousel slide carousel-fade&quot; data-ride=&quot;carousel&quot; data-interval=&quot;2500&quot;&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-inner&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-item active&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/colored-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pattern 1&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-item&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/colored-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pattern 2&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-item&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/colored-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pattern 3&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-item&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/colored-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pattern 4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;a class=&quot;carousel-control-prev&quot; href=&quot;#carouselTruchetColored&quot; role=&quot;button&quot; data-slide=&quot;prev&quot;&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;carousel-control-prev-icon&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;sr-only&quot;&gt;Previous&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;a class=&quot;carousel-control-next&quot; href=&quot;#carouselTruchetColored&quot; role=&quot;button&quot; data-slide=&quot;next&quot;&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;carousel-control-next-icon&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;sr-only&quot;&gt;Next&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The addition of colour not only makes the patterns much more interesting to look at, but differentiates them even further from each other, taking us further and further from the basic tiles we started with. The beauty and complexity of the final artwork disguises the simplicity of the building blocks - a statement that is true of the simple patterns seen in this post, but also, I think, of generative art as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Stephens</name><email>alex.stephens@eng.ox.ac.uk</email></author><summary type="html">What is generative art? Generative art refers to any art practice where the artist uses a system, such as a set of natural language rules, a computer program, a machine, or other procedural invention, which is set into motion with some degree of autonomy contributing to or resulting in a completed work of art. Philip Galanter Since first learning of the concept of generative art, I have been intrigued by what it has to offer. The idea of creating art with computer programs in particular caught my interest, since this is a medium that is both familiar and accessible to me. Experimenting with it myself, with the help of a variety of online resources, revealed the rich possibilities of creating visually satisfying artworks from foundations of algorithms and mathematics. The process of generating art programmatically typically involves randomness and tuneable parameters, making it highly dynamic and iterative. As I experimented I found I was often surprised by the results that came from changing parameters in my code, leading me to ideas that were not part of my original vision. Equally fun is looking at other peoples’ generated artworks, and trying to deduce what algorithms or mathematical concepts might have been used to create them. There are plenty of resources online that explain in more detail what generative art really is, and the many different tools and techniques that are used to create it, so these aspects won’t be the focus here (although if you are interested in a broader introduction to generative art, this article is excellent). The aim of this post is to demonstrate how an extremely simple base element or idea can be iterated upon to generate patterns that are (in my opinion, at least) surprisingly complex and pleasing to the eye. Generating a simple pattern To start off, let’s have a look at an example of a generative art pattern, which I created using the Javascript library p5.js. Looks pretty nice, right? Take a minute to look carefully at the image above, and think about this key question - how would you recreate the pattern? We want to come up with a plain English description of how one could go about producing something that looks like this. Can you come up with a simple process that would achieve this? The solution is probably a lot simpler than you’re thinking - the solutions that I went to at first were definitely unnecessarily complex. In fact, all you need to construct the pattern is the two tiles shown below, each consisting of a pair of opposing quarter circles. They’re really the same tile, just with a 90 degree rotational offset between them. To make this a bit clearer, here’s the original pattern again, this time with the tiles outlined: When I first saw this, which is an example of something called a Truchet pattern, I was pretty amazed by how simple it was to create. I was intrigued by the fact that it was not obvious from looking at the pattern how one would go about reproducing it, and yet once I found out the solution it was suddenly so simple. This, I think, is important in many types of generative art - the underlying ideas are often not as complex as they might seem at first. Developing the pattern So what else can we do with this type of pattern? One way to extend the design is by layering the pattern at multiple scales, using different shades and line thicknesses to create aesthetic variation. Previous Next Part of the beauty of generating art from code is that once the base program is written, modifications of this type (scaling, layering, etc.) are quick and easy. This is part of why the genre lends itself so well to experimentation, either manually or through randomisation. Finally, let’s add some colour. Shown below are a few more layered Truchet patterns, created with somewhat randomised sizes and scales. Previous Next The addition of colour not only makes the patterns much more interesting to look at, but differentiates them even further from each other, taking us further and further from the basic tiles we started with. The beauty and complexity of the final artwork disguises the simplicity of the building blocks - a statement that is true of the simple patterns seen in this post, but also, I think, of generative art as a whole.</summary></entry></feed>