<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-11T21:26:23+00:00</updated><id>https://alex-stephens.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alex Stephens</title><subtitle>Alex Stephens</subtitle><author><name>Alex Stephens</name><email>stephens@robots.ox.ac.uk</email></author><entry><title type="html">2020 Retrospective</title><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/2020-retro/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2020 Retrospective" /><published>2021-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-01-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/2020-retro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/2020-retro/">&lt;p&gt;I’ve never really been one for actively reflecting on my personal life, but as I sit here in my flat in Oxford under Tier 4 lockdown as the shit-show of 2020 comes to an end, this seems like as good a time as any to start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post will be a brief overview of what happened in my life this year, some reflections on various aspects of my personal life, and at the end we’ll look forwards at what I want to focus on in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;timeline&quot;&gt;Timeline&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with a quick overview of what actually happened in my life this year…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;big-picture&quot;&gt;Big picture&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started the year by returning to Australia after 6 months in California.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Submitted my thesis, completing my undergraduate studies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;8 months of casual work and chill time during the reign of COVID-19.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moved to Oxford in September for first term of PhD at University of Oxford&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;january&quot;&gt;January&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Returned to Australia after 6 months working at the NASA JPL in California.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Australia’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2019%E2%80%9320_Australian_bushfire_season&quot;&gt;bushfire crisis&lt;/a&gt; was at its height at the start of the year, but tapered off by the end of January.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Submitted my undergraduate thesis, marking the official end of my studies at the University of Sydney.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Submitted applications for a PhD in robotics at Oxford.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;february-april&quot;&gt;February-April&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Bushfires were quickly replaced by new, &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/2021-01-04-2020-retro/waves.jpg&quot;&gt;more exciting disasters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resumed my casual job as a tutor at the University of Sydney for the semester, which was moved online halfway through – got to experience the joy of online online (there were a few upsides, but mostly it sucked).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interviewed for Oxford, got accepted (!) and &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/2021-01-04-2020-retro/funding.jpg&quot;&gt;secured funding&lt;/a&gt;, meaning I would be moving my life to the UK in September.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;may-august&quot;&gt;May-August&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Graduation ceremony cancelled due to COVID.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plans for celebratory end-of-uni travel also dashed by COVID.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Relatively uneventful months – finished teaching at the uni, but Sydney was in lockdown so lived a quiet life at home and did a lot of gaming.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Managed to start &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?t=94&amp;amp;v=jl17CYYSzUw&quot;&gt;getting my shit together&lt;/a&gt; – further discussion below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;september-october&quot;&gt;September-October&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Moved from Sydney to Oxford.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Matriculated as a student at Exeter College, Oxford.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started my first term as a student in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aims.robots.ox.ac.uk/&quot;&gt;AIMS CDT&lt;/a&gt; – teaching was online due to COVID, but ended up being pretty enjoyable regardless.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;november-december&quot;&gt;November-December&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Finished up first term at Oxford.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Celebrated my birthday and Christmas in Oxford amid various lockdowns and restrictions across the UK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;habit-development&quot;&gt;Habit development&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most significant positive changes I’ve made this year has definitely been introducing more structure and routine into my life – necessary adaptations as I came to the end of five years of university imposing that structure for me. By around mid-year, I had started to feel like the days were blurring together and I wasn’t really doing much worthwhile with my time. In the latter half of the year, I made decent progress towards changing this on a couple of fronts, though it’s still a work in progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the meta-level, I also gained a much deeper understanding of &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; I can change my own behaviours in ways that will last, thanks to James Clear’s excellent book &lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt;, as well as a couple of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;reading&quot;&gt;Reading&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first time in a while, I have actually built a consistent reading habit that will hopefully stick around for a while longer. I’ve discussed the mechanics of the habit formation in &lt;a href=&quot;https://alexstephens.net/blog/reading/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;, but overall this has been great – I’ve read a bunch of fantastic books in the last couple of months, and have plenty more that I want to read as soon as I can get around to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;note-taking&quot;&gt;Note-taking&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout my undergraduate studies, I was always deeply dissatisfied by how I (and most people) organised and stored digital notes. All notes on course material were stored away in some sub-sub-subfolder, and 99% of them were never looked at again, because there was no easy way to resurface anything. I became less convinced of the value of note-taking as my degree went on, and by the end I only really took notes in the couple of weeks leading up to exams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery of &lt;a href=&quot;https://roamresearch.com/&quot;&gt;Roam Research&lt;/a&gt; in the last couple of months has been an absolute game-changer on this front, not just for academic note-taking, but for storing thoughts on &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt; – i.e. digital Personal Knowledge Management (PKM), or “building a second brain”. Roam completely does away with the hierarchical structure of traditional knowledge systems, instead treating all notes as nodes in a graph which can be linked to each other arbitrarily. This lowers the friction of note-taking, since there is no need to worry about where a note fits within the structure, and more importantly, allows notes to be easily &lt;em&gt;resurfaced and linked to related notes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been genuinely life-changing to me, and I will definitely write a full post about it at some point, but the upshot of it is that I now have a solid system for taking notes on basically everything, and I use it all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TL;DR: taking notes on stuff is great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;putting-myself-out-there&quot;&gt;Putting myself out there&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I don’t have any aspirations toward internet fame or whatever, I have definitely come to appreciate this year the value of public self-expression, and have tried to push myself toward doing more of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made this website a couple of months ago mainly so that I would have this blog, as a place to publicly write about anything I want to write about at a given time – there isn’t really a plan, but the main thing is that whenever I do decide I want to write something, I can put it here. I have started using &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/astephens__&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt; a little, but would like to make more use of it to take part in conversations and connect with people online. I even started a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.instagram.com/astephens.photo/&quot;&gt;photography Instagram page&lt;/a&gt; (talk about sentences I never thought I’d say), as a way of keeping myself publicly accountable on my new quest to become decent at photography.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of these things have been especially life-changing thus far, but for now that’s really the point – it’s more about building the habit and the systems for putting stuff out there, and enjoying the process of doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflection&quot;&gt;Reflection&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section attempts to capture the things that were most important in shaping my experience of 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-im-grateful-for&quot;&gt;What I’m grateful for&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not having been directly affected by the coronavirus – neither myself nor any of my friends or family actually suffered a serious case of the virus (in Australia, I didn’t know anybody at all who tested positive), and living a few months in lockdown is far less than what millions of people went through in 2020.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My wonderful girlfriend’s willingness to move to the other side of the world with me, particularly with the added uncertainties of this year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New friends in a new country: moving to the UK for at least the next four years without ever having set foot in the country was a pretty big step, but all the great people I’ve met here already have made it feel like home pretty quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;accomplishments&quot;&gt;Accomplishments&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acceptance into University of Oxford in my preferred PhD program (!)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Completion of undergraduate studies at USyd, 1st class + University Medal.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not getting COVID-19 (as far as I know), woo!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;stuff-i-enjoyed-more-of-this-year&quot;&gt;Stuff I enjoyed more of this year&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gaming&lt;/strong&gt;: spending more time at home due to the coronavirus and only working part-time for a large chunk of the year meant I did quite a bit of gaming. Playing online multiplayer with friends was actually a great form of social activity for 2020, and I enjoyed gaming more than ever this year.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reading&lt;/strong&gt;: slowly started to repair my fractured attention span and spend less time scrolling mindlessly on the internet… books are great, who knew.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Podcasts&lt;/strong&gt;: although I’ve listened to podcasts in previous years, this year I listened &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; more, partly because I more or less stopped listening to music while running, and also because during the pandemic I took to daily walks as a way to get out of the house.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Photography&lt;/strong&gt;: after moving to Oxford, I felt that it might be nice to learn basic photography skills so I can capture some visual memories of my time here. Turns out I enjoy photography more than I’d expected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;focus-for-2021&quot;&gt;Focus for 2021&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never really felt that the whole New Year’s resolution thing was the way to go for me, but I thought it might be helpful to write down a few focus areas that I’d like to keep at the front of my mind in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;deep-work&quot;&gt;Deep work&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cal Newport’s book &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25744928-deep-work&quot;&gt;Deep Work&lt;/a&gt; makes a pretty compelling case for the value of blocking out time for focused work on intellectually demanding tasks on a regular basis. As I get deeper into research work for my PhD, I think working out a reliable system for this will be invaluable, so 2021 is the time to start fleshing out a system for this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;connecting-with-people&quot;&gt;Connecting with people&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moving to a place like Oxford is a huge opportunity, and I think pushing myself to get to know more people will be hugely beneficial (obviously there’s not much to be done while the pandemic remains ). For this goal, I am not so much interested in attending big social events (though these can obviously be good in other ways), but rather in making the effort to do stuff like getting coffee with people I don’t know super well, having people over for dinner, or similar activities in more intimate settings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;running&quot;&gt;Running&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early months of 2020, I started a half-marathon training plan, but ultimately (either due to overdoing it or just bad luck) got injured and ran much less than I’d hoped for the rest of the year. I’d like to do a better job of building up my running strength in 2021, maintain consistency, and hopefully even get to some races at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;reading-1&quot;&gt;Reading&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to make sure that I keep reading as a more or less daily thing, even when I get busy with uni work or whatever else throughout the year. Even if it’s only 15 minutes a day, this is infinitely better than giving up on the habit altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;in-summary&quot;&gt;In summary…&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I had to sum up my overall goal for how I want 2021 to look different to 2020, it’s that I want to be &lt;strong&gt;more intentional with how I act and how I spend my time&lt;/strong&gt; – more focus, more optimisation, more long-term thinking. We’ll see how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Stephens</name><email>stephens@robots.ox.ac.uk</email></author><summary type="html">I’ve never really been one for actively reflecting on my personal life, but as I sit here in my flat in Oxford under Tier 4 lockdown as the shit-show of 2020 comes to an end, this seems like as good a time as any to start. This post will be a brief overview of what happened in my life this year, some reflections on various aspects of my personal life, and at the end we’ll look forwards at what I want to focus on in 2021. Timeline Let’s start with a quick overview of what actually happened in my life this year… Big picture Started the year by returning to Australia after 6 months in California. Submitted my thesis, completing my undergraduate studies. 8 months of casual work and chill time during the reign of COVID-19. Moved to Oxford in September for first term of PhD at University of Oxford January Returned to Australia after 6 months working at the NASA JPL in California. Australia’s bushfire crisis was at its height at the start of the year, but tapered off by the end of January. Submitted my undergraduate thesis, marking the official end of my studies at the University of Sydney. Submitted applications for a PhD in robotics at Oxford. February-April Bushfires were quickly replaced by new, more exciting disasters. Resumed my casual job as a tutor at the University of Sydney for the semester, which was moved online halfway through – got to experience the joy of online online (there were a few upsides, but mostly it sucked). Interviewed for Oxford, got accepted (!) and secured funding, meaning I would be moving my life to the UK in September. May-August Graduation ceremony cancelled due to COVID. Plans for celebratory end-of-uni travel also dashed by COVID. Relatively uneventful months – finished teaching at the uni, but Sydney was in lockdown so lived a quiet life at home and did a lot of gaming. Managed to start getting my shit together – further discussion below. September-October Moved from Sydney to Oxford. Matriculated as a student at Exeter College, Oxford. Started my first term as a student in the AIMS CDT – teaching was online due to COVID, but ended up being pretty enjoyable regardless. November-December Finished up first term at Oxford. Celebrated my birthday and Christmas in Oxford amid various lockdowns and restrictions across the UK. Habit development One of the most significant positive changes I’ve made this year has definitely been introducing more structure and routine into my life – necessary adaptations as I came to the end of five years of university imposing that structure for me. By around mid-year, I had started to feel like the days were blurring together and I wasn’t really doing much worthwhile with my time. In the latter half of the year, I made decent progress towards changing this on a couple of fronts, though it’s still a work in progress. On the meta-level, I also gained a much deeper understanding of how I can change my own behaviours in ways that will last, thanks to James Clear’s excellent book Atomic Habits, as well as a couple of others. Reading For the first time in a while, I have actually built a consistent reading habit that will hopefully stick around for a while longer. I’ve discussed the mechanics of the habit formation in this post, but overall this has been great – I’ve read a bunch of fantastic books in the last couple of months, and have plenty more that I want to read as soon as I can get around to them. Note-taking Throughout my undergraduate studies, I was always deeply dissatisfied by how I (and most people) organised and stored digital notes. All notes on course material were stored away in some sub-sub-subfolder, and 99% of them were never looked at again, because there was no easy way to resurface anything. I became less convinced of the value of note-taking as my degree went on, and by the end I only really took notes in the couple of weeks leading up to exams. The discovery of Roam Research in the last couple of months has been an absolute game-changer on this front, not just for academic note-taking, but for storing thoughts on anything – i.e. digital Personal Knowledge Management (PKM), or “building a second brain”. Roam completely does away with the hierarchical structure of traditional knowledge systems, instead treating all notes as nodes in a graph which can be linked to each other arbitrarily. This lowers the friction of note-taking, since there is no need to worry about where a note fits within the structure, and more importantly, allows notes to be easily resurfaced and linked to related notes. This has been genuinely life-changing to me, and I will definitely write a full post about it at some point, but the upshot of it is that I now have a solid system for taking notes on basically everything, and I use it all the time. TL;DR: taking notes on stuff is great. Putting myself out there Although I don’t have any aspirations toward internet fame or whatever, I have definitely come to appreciate this year the value of public self-expression, and have tried to push myself toward doing more of it. I made this website a couple of months ago mainly so that I would have this blog, as a place to publicly write about anything I want to write about at a given time – there isn’t really a plan, but the main thing is that whenever I do decide I want to write something, I can put it here. I have started using Twitter a little, but would like to make more use of it to take part in conversations and connect with people online. I even started a photography Instagram page (talk about sentences I never thought I’d say), as a way of keeping myself publicly accountable on my new quest to become decent at photography. None of these things have been especially life-changing thus far, but for now that’s really the point – it’s more about building the habit and the systems for putting stuff out there, and enjoying the process of doing so. Reflection This section attempts to capture the things that were most important in shaping my experience of 2020. What I’m grateful for Not having been directly affected by the coronavirus – neither myself nor any of my friends or family actually suffered a serious case of the virus (in Australia, I didn’t know anybody at all who tested positive), and living a few months in lockdown is far less than what millions of people went through in 2020. My wonderful girlfriend’s willingness to move to the other side of the world with me, particularly with the added uncertainties of this year. New friends in a new country: moving to the UK for at least the next four years without ever having set foot in the country was a pretty big step, but all the great people I’ve met here already have made it feel like home pretty quickly. Accomplishments Acceptance into University of Oxford in my preferred PhD program (!) Completion of undergraduate studies at USyd, 1st class + University Medal. Not getting COVID-19 (as far as I know), woo! Stuff I enjoyed more of this year Gaming: spending more time at home due to the coronavirus and only working part-time for a large chunk of the year meant I did quite a bit of gaming. Playing online multiplayer with friends was actually a great form of social activity for 2020, and I enjoyed gaming more than ever this year. Reading: slowly started to repair my fractured attention span and spend less time scrolling mindlessly on the internet… books are great, who knew. Podcasts: although I’ve listened to podcasts in previous years, this year I listened way more, partly because I more or less stopped listening to music while running, and also because during the pandemic I took to daily walks as a way to get out of the house. Photography: after moving to Oxford, I felt that it might be nice to learn basic photography skills so I can capture some visual memories of my time here. Turns out I enjoy photography more than I’d expected. Focus for 2021 I’ve never really felt that the whole New Year’s resolution thing was the way to go for me, but I thought it might be helpful to write down a few focus areas that I’d like to keep at the front of my mind in 2021. Deep work Cal Newport’s book Deep Work makes a pretty compelling case for the value of blocking out time for focused work on intellectually demanding tasks on a regular basis. As I get deeper into research work for my PhD, I think working out a reliable system for this will be invaluable, so 2021 is the time to start fleshing out a system for this. Connecting with people Moving to a place like Oxford is a huge opportunity, and I think pushing myself to get to know more people will be hugely beneficial (obviously there’s not much to be done while the pandemic remains ). For this goal, I am not so much interested in attending big social events (though these can obviously be good in other ways), but rather in making the effort to do stuff like getting coffee with people I don’t know super well, having people over for dinner, or similar activities in more intimate settings. Running In the early months of 2020, I started a half-marathon training plan, but ultimately (either due to overdoing it or just bad luck) got injured and ran much less than I’d hoped for the rest of the year. I’d like to do a better job of building up my running strength in 2021, maintain consistency, and hopefully even get to some races at some point. Reading I want to make sure that I keep reading as a more or less daily thing, even when I get busy with uni work or whatever else throughout the year. Even if it’s only 15 minutes a day, this is infinitely better than giving up on the habit altogether. In summary… If I had to sum up my overall goal for how I want 2021 to look different to 2020, it’s that I want to be more intentional with how I act and how I spend my time – more focus, more optimisation, more long-term thinking. We’ll see how it goes.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">2020 Content Roundup</title><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/2020-roundup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2020 Content Roundup" /><published>2020-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/2020-roundup</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/2020-roundup/">&lt;p&gt;More so than many other years, I think it’s reasonable to say that my 2020 was shaped significantly by the various content I consumed, for reasons personal, circumstantial, and global-pandemic-related. As such I thought it might be fun to write up this little overview of the pieces that I enjoyed the most or that had the biggest impacts on me this year, if nothing else because it might be interesting to look back on further down the line.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;books&quot;&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;atomic-habits-by-james-clear&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/40121378-atomic-habits&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by James Clear&lt;/h6&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I’d heard many of the ideas from this book before, reading it in full gave me a new level of clarity on how habits are formed and maintained. I’ve already found the advice from this book hugely valuable on different levels in developing my habits for reading, running, and studying, and look forward to applying it to other areas in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;the-courage-to-be-disliked-by--ichiro-kishimi-and-fumitake-koga&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/43306206-the-courage-to-be-disliked&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Courage To Be Disliked&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by  Ichiro Kishimi and Fumitake Koga&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book genuinely changed the way I view interpersonal relationships and personal motivations, and gave me a whole new framework for thinking about how and why we express emotions to others. It’s written as a Socratic dialogue of sorts between a Youth and a Philosopher, which at first I found a little jarring, but quickly became one of the book’s strongest features. I really think that the ideas in this book have made a significant contribution to my ability to understand and empathise with others, though I only read it fairly recently so can’t really evaluate long-term effects just yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;the-silmarillion-by-j-r-r-tolkien&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/7332.The_Silmarillion&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Silmarillion&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by J. R. R. Tolkien&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a huge fan of &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; (books and movies), this one had been on my radar for a while, but I’d never got around to reading it, perhaps in part because of its reputation for being an extremely dense and challenging read. Now that I am living in Oxford, as a member of the same college where Tolkien himself was a student, it felt like the right time to finally give it a go, and – somewhat to my surprise – I actually found it pretty hard to put down once I started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story is truly epic in scope, describing the history of Middle-earth across the thousands of years following its creation as the backdrop for its central narrative thread about the tragic saga of three fabled gems called the Silmarils. &lt;em&gt;The Silmarillion&lt;/em&gt; presents Tolkien’s universe  at the grandest of scales, and really conveys the vastness and intricacy of the mythological world that he envisioned. It gave me a much greater appreciation of the context behind familiar events described in &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt;, enriching them with new layers of context through a story that was a true joy to experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020-12-31-2020-roundup/silmarillion.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;mans-search-for-meaning-by-victor-frankl&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/4069.Man_s_Search_for_Meaning&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Man’s Search for Meaning&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Victor Frankl&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this book, originally published in 1946, Frankl recounts his experiences as a prisoner in the Nazi concentration camps of WWII. A psychiatrist by profession, he describes how the experiences of everyday life in a concentration camp shaped the mind of the average prisoner. Despite the horror of the experiences he describes, the book is profoundly hopeful in nature, arguing that meaning be found even in a life of suffering, and that we always have the freedom to choose how we cope with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;deep-work-by-cal-newport-&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/25744928-deep-work&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deep Work&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Cal Newport *&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s probably fair to say that most of us are aware on some level that the constant distractions of mobile phones and the internet are highly destructive to our attention span and ability to focus for extended periods. Although I’d thought about this issue a fair bit previously, this book gave me a much clearer understanding of how this distractedness affects my productivity, and – importantly – a lot of actionable advice and tips on how to reclaim my ability to focus this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* &lt;em&gt;This book is more of an honourable mention on this list, since I read it quite recently and haven’t had the chance to try implementing much of its advice yet – I aim to do so as I transition into full-time PhD research in the latter half of 2021. Ideally, by the end of my PhD I’ll have successfully implemented a significant portion of the book’s recommended behaviours into my regular workflow, and will be able to look back on it as a turning point for my academic productivity… A man’s gotta have dreams, right?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;online-content-creators&quot;&gt;Online Content Creators&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;ali-abdaal-youtube-and-not-overthinking-podcast&quot;&gt;Ali Abdaal (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/aliabdaal&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://notoverthinking.com/&quot;&gt;Not Overthinking&lt;/a&gt; podcast)&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ali is a Cambridge-medicine-graduate-turned-YouTuber who makes videos about productivity, creativity, or general thoughts on how to lead a happier and more fulfilling life. The discovery of Ali’s content on YouTube in the latter half of 2020 was a real game changer for me. For the most part, his worldview aligns quite well with my own, as such I’ve found that a lot of his tips and advice have been things that I could readily incorporate into my life to improve it in various ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last few months, I feel that I have become more organised, (somewhat) more sociable, and more confident, and more productive, particularly with respect to how I spend my free time. Ali’s content has contributed significantly to all of these by making me think actively and critically about aspects of my life when otherwise I might not have. The Not Overthinking podcast, presented by Ali and his brother Taimur, has been my favourite listening material on my walks and runs for the last couple of months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;ben-parkes-youtube&quot;&gt;Ben Parkes (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/benparkes&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ben is a UK-based athlete who makes videos about his training, lifestyle and experiences as a sub-elite runner. I discovered him  in early 2019, shortly after I started running regularly myself, and his videos have been a source of both motivation and valuable information ever since. This year, he broke his ankle – as you can imagine, devastating for a serious runner – but rather than being deterred, worked harder than ever to get himself back up to full strength as quickly and safely as possible. Having struggled a fair bit with persistent (although much smaller) injuries this year, Ben’s content was helpful as ever to follow along with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;peter-mckinnon-youtube&quot;&gt;Peter McKinnon (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/petermckinnon&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter McKinnon is a Canadian photographer and filmmaker with an extremely popular YouTube channel, where he documents his various photography projects, workflows, and editing techniques. In the span of just a few videos, Peter McKinnon more or less convinced me that I wanted to start out with photography. His videos quickly taught me a lot about both photography and editing, eventually prompting me to buy a small mirrorless camera and start messing around with it. I’ve thoroughly enjoyed exploring town on photo walks, thinking about out how to get the best shots, and then coming home to mess around with them in Lightroom and Photoshop. Definitely keen to carry on learning!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;movies-and-tv&quot;&gt;Movies and TV&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was actually a fairly light year for me in movies and TV. For obvious reasons, I didn’t go to the cinema nearly as much as usual this year, and overall didn’t watch many new shows either. From those I did watch, there were a few that really stood out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;tenet&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tenet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As both a Christopher Nolan enthusiast and a physics nerd, this was easily the movie I was most looking forward to this year, and it didn’t disappoint (… controversial take?). The central idea of temporal inversion was taken to a lot of interesting places throughout the film, and even though the grounding in real science was fairly limited (compared with, for example, &lt;em&gt;Interstellar&lt;/em&gt;), it was clear Nolan had at least given it plenty of thought. The movie’s aesthetic was great, many of the action sequences were truly mind-blowing, and I appreciated that the audience’s hand wasn’t held too tightly through the complexities of the plot. I saw Tenet twice in cinemas, enjoyed it even more on second viewing, and expect it to have excellent rewatch value for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020-12-31-2020-roundup/tenet.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;the-boys&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Boys&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was a little late to the party here, but this was one of those few shows that I was utterly hooked on about 10 minutes into the first episode. As a fan of superhero movies generally, this show is a refreshing new angle on the genre. It’s consistently fast-paced, has loads of distinctive characters whose interactions are a joy to watch, and pulls absolutely no punches with its dark twists and relentless violence. Can’t wait for season 3 (hopefully) in 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;brooklyn-nine-nine&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Brooklyn Nine-Nine&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one’s been a favourite of mine for a few years now, but deserved a spot on this list anyway for how much I’ve enjoyed it this year. Its seventh season, which came out in February, was as fantastic as any of the previous ones, continuing to add new depth to its core characters while providing a great balance of lighthearted comedy and poignant exploration of serious issues. Always great to see a show that’s run for this long continuing to provide some of its best episodes with each new season.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gaming&quot;&gt;Gaming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;apex-legends&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Apex Legends&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve done a decent amount of gaming over the years, but there aren’t many games I’ve logged more than 500 hours on, let alone in the span of only about a year playing them. The in-game communication system is a cut above any other online multiplayer I’ve experienced, and really lent itself to tactical play-styles that kept the game feeling fresh even after hundreds of hours in game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;doom-eternal&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;DOOM Eternal&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This game is an absolute tour de force in game design. The combat system is brilliant, with a high skill ceiling that makes it ever more rewarding to rip and tear through hordes of demons as you master the tools at your disposal.
The campaign takes no more than 15 hours to complete, yet I racked up over 150 hours in it and loved every minute. I often enjoy tackling games on high difficulty settings, but DOOM Eternal was the first game for which I’d ever felt tempted to tackle a permadeath mode (a difficulty level called “Ultra Nightmare”, in which you have to make it through the entire campaign on the hardest settings &lt;em&gt;without dying once&lt;/em&gt;). The journey to completing the game on Ultra Nightmare was a genuinely great experience, which pushed me towards mastery of the combat mechanics without feeling at all like a repetitive grind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/2020-12-31-2020-roundup/doom.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;miscellaneous&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h6 id=&quot;trying-to-try-by-eliezer-yudkowsky&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/WLJwTJ7uGPA5Qphbp/trying-to-try&quot;&gt;Trying to Try&lt;/a&gt; by Eliezer Yudkowsky&lt;/h6&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This blog post was easily one of the best things I read this year, and it felt wrong to leave it off this list – I’ll probably write a full post discussing it in more depth some point. It explores the idea that we often don’t hold ourselves to high enough standards, and instead slip into a mindset where we will half-heartedly attempt something, fail, but convince ourselves “well, I tried” and be satisfied with that – we don’t really want to put in the work required to succeed, we just want to feel like we’ve tried so we don’t feel bad about &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; trying. Yudkowsky writes that “often where succeeding to do a thing is very hard, trying to do it is much easier”, a sentiment that I’ve found is reflected in my actions more often than I’d like to admit. The article isn’t a long read, but since reading it I have started noticing this “trying to try” mentality all over the place.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Stephens</name><email>stephens@robots.ox.ac.uk</email></author><summary type="html">More so than many other years, I think it’s reasonable to say that my 2020 was shaped significantly by the various content I consumed, for reasons personal, circumstantial, and global-pandemic-related. As such I thought it might be fun to write up this little overview of the pieces that I enjoyed the most or that had the biggest impacts on me this year, if nothing else because it might be interesting to look back on further down the line. Books Atomic Habits by James Clear Although I’d heard many of the ideas from this book before, reading it in full gave me a new level of clarity on how habits are formed and maintained. I’ve already found the advice from this book hugely valuable on different levels in developing my habits for reading, running, and studying, and look forward to applying it to other areas in the future. The Courage To Be Disliked by Ichiro Kishimi and Fumitake Koga This book genuinely changed the way I view interpersonal relationships and personal motivations, and gave me a whole new framework for thinking about how and why we express emotions to others. It’s written as a Socratic dialogue of sorts between a Youth and a Philosopher, which at first I found a little jarring, but quickly became one of the book’s strongest features. I really think that the ideas in this book have made a significant contribution to my ability to understand and empathise with others, though I only read it fairly recently so can’t really evaluate long-term effects just yet. The Silmarillion by J. R. R. Tolkien As a huge fan of The Lord of the Rings (books and movies), this one had been on my radar for a while, but I’d never got around to reading it, perhaps in part because of its reputation for being an extremely dense and challenging read. Now that I am living in Oxford, as a member of the same college where Tolkien himself was a student, it felt like the right time to finally give it a go, and – somewhat to my surprise – I actually found it pretty hard to put down once I started. The story is truly epic in scope, describing the history of Middle-earth across the thousands of years following its creation as the backdrop for its central narrative thread about the tragic saga of three fabled gems called the Silmarils. The Silmarillion presents Tolkien’s universe at the grandest of scales, and really conveys the vastness and intricacy of the mythological world that he envisioned. It gave me a much greater appreciation of the context behind familiar events described in The Lord of the Rings, enriching them with new layers of context through a story that was a true joy to experience. Man’s Search for Meaning by Victor Frankl In this book, originally published in 1946, Frankl recounts his experiences as a prisoner in the Nazi concentration camps of WWII. A psychiatrist by profession, he describes how the experiences of everyday life in a concentration camp shaped the mind of the average prisoner. Despite the horror of the experiences he describes, the book is profoundly hopeful in nature, arguing that meaning be found even in a life of suffering, and that we always have the freedom to choose how we cope with it. Deep Work by Cal Newport * It’s probably fair to say that most of us are aware on some level that the constant distractions of mobile phones and the internet are highly destructive to our attention span and ability to focus for extended periods. Although I’d thought about this issue a fair bit previously, this book gave me a much clearer understanding of how this distractedness affects my productivity, and – importantly – a lot of actionable advice and tips on how to reclaim my ability to focus this. * This book is more of an honourable mention on this list, since I read it quite recently and haven’t had the chance to try implementing much of its advice yet – I aim to do so as I transition into full-time PhD research in the latter half of 2021. Ideally, by the end of my PhD I’ll have successfully implemented a significant portion of the book’s recommended behaviours into my regular workflow, and will be able to look back on it as a turning point for my academic productivity… A man’s gotta have dreams, right? Online Content Creators Ali Abdaal (YouTube and Not Overthinking podcast) Ali is a Cambridge-medicine-graduate-turned-YouTuber who makes videos about productivity, creativity, or general thoughts on how to lead a happier and more fulfilling life. The discovery of Ali’s content on YouTube in the latter half of 2020 was a real game changer for me. For the most part, his worldview aligns quite well with my own, as such I’ve found that a lot of his tips and advice have been things that I could readily incorporate into my life to improve it in various ways. In the last few months, I feel that I have become more organised, (somewhat) more sociable, and more confident, and more productive, particularly with respect to how I spend my free time. Ali’s content has contributed significantly to all of these by making me think actively and critically about aspects of my life when otherwise I might not have. The Not Overthinking podcast, presented by Ali and his brother Taimur, has been my favourite listening material on my walks and runs for the last couple of months. Ben Parkes (YouTube) Ben is a UK-based athlete who makes videos about his training, lifestyle and experiences as a sub-elite runner. I discovered him in early 2019, shortly after I started running regularly myself, and his videos have been a source of both motivation and valuable information ever since. This year, he broke his ankle – as you can imagine, devastating for a serious runner – but rather than being deterred, worked harder than ever to get himself back up to full strength as quickly and safely as possible. Having struggled a fair bit with persistent (although much smaller) injuries this year, Ben’s content was helpful as ever to follow along with. Peter McKinnon (YouTube) Peter McKinnon is a Canadian photographer and filmmaker with an extremely popular YouTube channel, where he documents his various photography projects, workflows, and editing techniques. In the span of just a few videos, Peter McKinnon more or less convinced me that I wanted to start out with photography. His videos quickly taught me a lot about both photography and editing, eventually prompting me to buy a small mirrorless camera and start messing around with it. I’ve thoroughly enjoyed exploring town on photo walks, thinking about out how to get the best shots, and then coming home to mess around with them in Lightroom and Photoshop. Definitely keen to carry on learning! Movies and TV This was actually a fairly light year for me in movies and TV. For obvious reasons, I didn’t go to the cinema nearly as much as usual this year, and overall didn’t watch many new shows either. From those I did watch, there were a few that really stood out. Tenet As both a Christopher Nolan enthusiast and a physics nerd, this was easily the movie I was most looking forward to this year, and it didn’t disappoint (… controversial take?). The central idea of temporal inversion was taken to a lot of interesting places throughout the film, and even though the grounding in real science was fairly limited (compared with, for example, Interstellar), it was clear Nolan had at least given it plenty of thought. The movie’s aesthetic was great, many of the action sequences were truly mind-blowing, and I appreciated that the audience’s hand wasn’t held too tightly through the complexities of the plot. I saw Tenet twice in cinemas, enjoyed it even more on second viewing, and expect it to have excellent rewatch value for years to come. The Boys I was a little late to the party here, but this was one of those few shows that I was utterly hooked on about 10 minutes into the first episode. As a fan of superhero movies generally, this show is a refreshing new angle on the genre. It’s consistently fast-paced, has loads of distinctive characters whose interactions are a joy to watch, and pulls absolutely no punches with its dark twists and relentless violence. Can’t wait for season 3 (hopefully) in 2021. Brooklyn Nine-Nine This one’s been a favourite of mine for a few years now, but deserved a spot on this list anyway for how much I’ve enjoyed it this year. Its seventh season, which came out in February, was as fantastic as any of the previous ones, continuing to add new depth to its core characters while providing a great balance of lighthearted comedy and poignant exploration of serious issues. Always great to see a show that’s run for this long continuing to provide some of its best episodes with each new season. Gaming Apex Legends I’ve done a decent amount of gaming over the years, but there aren’t many games I’ve logged more than 500 hours on, let alone in the span of only about a year playing them. The in-game communication system is a cut above any other online multiplayer I’ve experienced, and really lent itself to tactical play-styles that kept the game feeling fresh even after hundreds of hours in game. DOOM Eternal This game is an absolute tour de force in game design. The combat system is brilliant, with a high skill ceiling that makes it ever more rewarding to rip and tear through hordes of demons as you master the tools at your disposal. The campaign takes no more than 15 hours to complete, yet I racked up over 150 hours in it and loved every minute. I often enjoy tackling games on high difficulty settings, but DOOM Eternal was the first game for which I’d ever felt tempted to tackle a permadeath mode (a difficulty level called “Ultra Nightmare”, in which you have to make it through the entire campaign on the hardest settings without dying once). The journey to completing the game on Ultra Nightmare was a genuinely great experience, which pushed me towards mastery of the combat mechanics without feeling at all like a repetitive grind. Miscellaneous Trying to Try by Eliezer Yudkowsky This blog post was easily one of the best things I read this year, and it felt wrong to leave it off this list – I’ll probably write a full post discussing it in more depth some point. It explores the idea that we often don’t hold ourselves to high enough standards, and instead slip into a mindset where we will half-heartedly attempt something, fail, but convince ourselves “well, I tried” and be satisfied with that – we don’t really want to put in the work required to succeed, we just want to feel like we’ve tried so we don’t feel bad about not trying. Yudkowsky writes that “often where succeeding to do a thing is very hard, trying to do it is much easier”, a sentiment that I’ve found is reflected in my actions more often than I’d like to admit. The article isn’t a long read, but since reading it I have started noticing this “trying to try” mentality all over the place.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Goodhart’s Law: How Not to Read More Books</title><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/reading/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Goodhart’s Law: How Not to Read More Books" /><published>2020-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/reading</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/reading/">&lt;p&gt;At some point in our lives, most of us have had the thought “I should try to read more” . In the current of era distractedness, where everything and everyone is competing for our attention in real time, it can be hard to just sit down and read a good old-fashioned book. It’s not that I don’t like reading - in fact, I enjoy it a lot, and it’s pretty clear to me that spending more time reading would be a good thing - it’s more just a problem of prioritisation and attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last couple of months, I’ve been more or less able to re-establish my reading routine to a level that I’m happy with for now, and confident that I will be able to maintain or build upon.  In this time, I’ve also tried to learn a bit about how to go about reading more in an effective manner, as well as more generally how to establish habits that will stick. This post reflects on the advice I’ve come across and behaviour changes I’ve implemented over the last few months towards this aim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-that-havent-helped&quot;&gt;Things that haven’t helped&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the common threads that comes up when you look for advice online on how to read more is videos or blog posts with titles like “How I Read 100 Books in a Year”. Some of these actually contain great advice, but I do feel that the way they are framed - with &lt;strong&gt;reading more books&lt;/strong&gt; as the primary goal - is somewhat problematic. When you set this goal for yourself, there are side-effects that reduce the value you actually get from the act of the reading, and might even eventually discourage you from reading as much in the long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of key problems that arise from the goal of reading more books, which I’ve tried to consciously push back against:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preference for shorter books&lt;/strong&gt;. Clearly, if you want to get through more books, you should pick shorter ones. Unfortunately, many of the great books out there are &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; the short ones, and picking books using this heuristic will encourage you towards less interesting books.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preference for easier books&lt;/strong&gt;. In a similar vein, you’ll get through books quicker if you can read them at full speed. This is less than ideal, since books that you find easier to read will tend to be the ones that don’t require much thought, and will therefore be less valuable to you overall.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unwillingness to slow down&lt;/strong&gt;. In all of the most impactful books I’ve read, the ones that really changed my view of the world in some way, the best bits made me &lt;em&gt;slow down&lt;/em&gt;. When you come across a passage, idea, or chapter that really resonates you, it makes sense to read it more slowly and deliberately, giving yourself time to properly engage with what you’re reading. Relatedly, the aim of getting through more books discourages you from stopping to take notes, which I’ll talk about more later on.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think there are many people out there who would say “I don’t want to read more books”, yet it does seem like the goal of reading more books can be somewhat problematic. This can be understood through a concept called &lt;em&gt;Goodhart’s law&lt;/em&gt;, which is sometimes expressed as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that we set the goal of reading more books with the intention of &lt;em&gt;contributing more overall value to our lives through reading&lt;/em&gt;, but as soon as we start changing our behaviour to specifically target that goal of reading more books, we side-step many of the qualities that make reading valuable in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;things-that-have-helped&quot;&gt;Things that have helped&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the question now is, what &lt;strong&gt;should&lt;/strong&gt; you focus on if your aim is to get more value out of reading? So far, I’ve found that the most helpful changes to either my worldview or my reading habits have been ones that (a) make me &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to read more, or (b) optimise the reading process for my mood and interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the things that have helped me the most so far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Giving up on books I don’t like&lt;/strong&gt;. Over the years, I’ve acquired the idea that books deserve some level of “respect”, respect that we don’t give to other media like news articles or online videos, which usually meant feeling an obligation to finish books that I’d started. This meant that if I got bored of a book halfway through, it would take me weeks or months to finish it because I never felt like sitting down and reading while I was still on this one book. As a result, I’d read almost nothing during that time, whereas if I’d been willing to just give up on that book and move onto something new I could’ve read loads more.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Skimming the slow bits&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’re reading a book that’s several hundred pages long, chances are that even if it’s a good book, not all of it is equally interesting and relevant to you. Nowadays, when I come to one of these slow points - perhaps a chapter that covers a general idea I’m already familiar with - I’ll flick through it quickly, spending just enough time on each page to get the general idea. If something jumps out at me, I’ll slow down again, but this realisation that skimming is a useful tool even in recreational reading has been a game changer. I’ve applied this one mostly to non-fiction so far, but I think it could help with some types of fiction as well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reading multiple books at a time&lt;/strong&gt;. What I feel like reading at any given moment can vary pretty wildly - it could be that when I started on that 300 page book on the history of calculus, it was exactly what I felt like reading, but that probably won’t be the case every day for the following week or two. To overcome this dilemma, I’ve taken to starting new books without necessarily finishing the previous ones. This means that on a given day, I can read whatever I most feel like at the time, or start a new book if I’d rather do that. Again, I’ve only applied this to non-fiction books which didn’t have too complex of an overarching narrative, so I didn’t really notice any negative side-effects, but I suspect reading more than one or two fiction books at the same time could be a bit trickier.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Having a reading list&lt;/strong&gt;. Keeping a proper database of books that I decided at some point I might like to read in the future has been very helpful. It means I’ll never reach a point where I don’t know what I want to read next, and instead can always come up with a couple of books that I’m excited to start on.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Going digital&lt;/strong&gt;. This one probably isn’t for everyone, but for me, switching to reading everything on Kindle has been great. Now, all of my books are in one place, I can take them anywhere really easily, and when I decide on a new book it takes me all of about 30 seconds to buy and download it. This has also helped a lot with the next point…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Taking notes&lt;/strong&gt;. What’s the point of reading a (non-fiction) book if you’re just going to forget it all? I’ve found that taking notes as I read, and then doing a bit of a reflection on the book afterwards, has helped me to engage a lot better with the books I read, and also meant that I can easily refer to my notes if I want to recall the key insights I got from each book. Using an ebook reader also lets me highlight notes directly in the books I read, and I can easily go back to these highlights whenever I want.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Incorporating it into my daily routine&lt;/strong&gt;. This is typically the first bit of advice you’d hear on how to read more - “read a bit each night before bed”, or something along those lines. Well, it’s good advice, so here it is again. Personally, I’ve made it a rule that I will read for at least 10 minutes every night right before I go to sleep. Not only is this a nice, relaxing way to end the day, but most of the time I end up reading for a fair bit longer anyway - as is often the case, the most important thing is just showing up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing that ties all of these things together is that they all focus on the &lt;strong&gt;process&lt;/strong&gt; of reading, rather than the goal of reading more. In the book &lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt;, James Clear gives this advice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;If you want better results, then forget about setting goals. Focus on your system instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clear argues that the long-term positive behaviour change must rely on &lt;strong&gt;systems&lt;/strong&gt; rather than goals: “You do not rise to the level of your goals. You fall to the level of your systems.” The habits and attitude shifts listed above have meant that I read more in the last few months than I had at any point in the last few years. More importantly, by optimising the reading process and eliminating some of the associated mental blocks, I am able to enjoy the books I read much more, and as a result also get more value out of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;towards-better-reading&quot;&gt;Towards better reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The upshot of all of this is that by eliminating a bunch of the obstacles to reading consistently, then adopting habits that make reading more fun and incorporating them into my daily routine, I have been able to read more, read better, and enjoy it more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than focusing on macroscopic goals like getting through a new book each week, I’ve prioritised simply showing up each day, and creating a system that makes it easy and fun to do so. At any given time, there will be a book on my Kindle that I am keen to read more of, and without the self-imposed pressure to get through it quickly, I can read at a pace that optimises for both enjoyment and value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are definitely still other avenues I’d like to explore with improving my reading habits. Lots of people swear by audiobooks these days - I personally have tried and enjoyed a handful of them, but mostly tended to prefer podcasts since they are freely available, while audiobooks are a little expensive for my liking. I also hope to experiment with reading some more “challenging” books, in whatever form that might take, with the aim of exploring a little deeper into unfamiliar ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, though, all of the small habit changes and attitude shifts described in this post have already had a huge cumulative effect on my reading in the last few months, and I’m keen to see where I can take them from here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Stephens</name><email>stephens@robots.ox.ac.uk</email></author><summary type="html">At some point in our lives, most of us have had the thought “I should try to read more” . In the current of era distractedness, where everything and everyone is competing for our attention in real time, it can be hard to just sit down and read a good old-fashioned book. It’s not that I don’t like reading - in fact, I enjoy it a lot, and it’s pretty clear to me that spending more time reading would be a good thing - it’s more just a problem of prioritisation and attention. In the last couple of months, I’ve been more or less able to re-establish my reading routine to a level that I’m happy with for now, and confident that I will be able to maintain or build upon. In this time, I’ve also tried to learn a bit about how to go about reading more in an effective manner, as well as more generally how to establish habits that will stick. This post reflects on the advice I’ve come across and behaviour changes I’ve implemented over the last few months towards this aim. Things that haven’t helped One of the common threads that comes up when you look for advice online on how to read more is videos or blog posts with titles like “How I Read 100 Books in a Year”. Some of these actually contain great advice, but I do feel that the way they are framed - with reading more books as the primary goal - is somewhat problematic. When you set this goal for yourself, there are side-effects that reduce the value you actually get from the act of the reading, and might even eventually discourage you from reading as much in the long term. There are a couple of key problems that arise from the goal of reading more books, which I’ve tried to consciously push back against: Preference for shorter books. Clearly, if you want to get through more books, you should pick shorter ones. Unfortunately, many of the great books out there are not the short ones, and picking books using this heuristic will encourage you towards less interesting books. Preference for easier books. In a similar vein, you’ll get through books quicker if you can read them at full speed. This is less than ideal, since books that you find easier to read will tend to be the ones that don’t require much thought, and will therefore be less valuable to you overall. Unwillingness to slow down. In all of the most impactful books I’ve read, the ones that really changed my view of the world in some way, the best bits made me slow down. When you come across a passage, idea, or chapter that really resonates you, it makes sense to read it more slowly and deliberately, giving yourself time to properly engage with what you’re reading. Relatedly, the aim of getting through more books discourages you from stopping to take notes, which I’ll talk about more later on. I don’t think there are many people out there who would say “I don’t want to read more books”, yet it does seem like the goal of reading more books can be somewhat problematic. This can be understood through a concept called Goodhart’s law, which is sometimes expressed as follows: When a measure becomes a target, it ceases to be a good measure. The problem is that we set the goal of reading more books with the intention of contributing more overall value to our lives through reading, but as soon as we start changing our behaviour to specifically target that goal of reading more books, we side-step many of the qualities that make reading valuable in the first place. Things that have helped So the question now is, what should you focus on if your aim is to get more value out of reading? So far, I’ve found that the most helpful changes to either my worldview or my reading habits have been ones that (a) make me want to read more, or (b) optimise the reading process for my mood and interests. Some of the things that have helped me the most so far: Giving up on books I don’t like. Over the years, I’ve acquired the idea that books deserve some level of “respect”, respect that we don’t give to other media like news articles or online videos, which usually meant feeling an obligation to finish books that I’d started. This meant that if I got bored of a book halfway through, it would take me weeks or months to finish it because I never felt like sitting down and reading while I was still on this one book. As a result, I’d read almost nothing during that time, whereas if I’d been willing to just give up on that book and move onto something new I could’ve read loads more. Skimming the slow bits. If you’re reading a book that’s several hundred pages long, chances are that even if it’s a good book, not all of it is equally interesting and relevant to you. Nowadays, when I come to one of these slow points - perhaps a chapter that covers a general idea I’m already familiar with - I’ll flick through it quickly, spending just enough time on each page to get the general idea. If something jumps out at me, I’ll slow down again, but this realisation that skimming is a useful tool even in recreational reading has been a game changer. I’ve applied this one mostly to non-fiction so far, but I think it could help with some types of fiction as well. Reading multiple books at a time. What I feel like reading at any given moment can vary pretty wildly - it could be that when I started on that 300 page book on the history of calculus, it was exactly what I felt like reading, but that probably won’t be the case every day for the following week or two. To overcome this dilemma, I’ve taken to starting new books without necessarily finishing the previous ones. This means that on a given day, I can read whatever I most feel like at the time, or start a new book if I’d rather do that. Again, I’ve only applied this to non-fiction books which didn’t have too complex of an overarching narrative, so I didn’t really notice any negative side-effects, but I suspect reading more than one or two fiction books at the same time could be a bit trickier. Having a reading list. Keeping a proper database of books that I decided at some point I might like to read in the future has been very helpful. It means I’ll never reach a point where I don’t know what I want to read next, and instead can always come up with a couple of books that I’m excited to start on. Going digital. This one probably isn’t for everyone, but for me, switching to reading everything on Kindle has been great. Now, all of my books are in one place, I can take them anywhere really easily, and when I decide on a new book it takes me all of about 30 seconds to buy and download it. This has also helped a lot with the next point… Taking notes. What’s the point of reading a (non-fiction) book if you’re just going to forget it all? I’ve found that taking notes as I read, and then doing a bit of a reflection on the book afterwards, has helped me to engage a lot better with the books I read, and also meant that I can easily refer to my notes if I want to recall the key insights I got from each book. Using an ebook reader also lets me highlight notes directly in the books I read, and I can easily go back to these highlights whenever I want. Incorporating it into my daily routine. This is typically the first bit of advice you’d hear on how to read more - “read a bit each night before bed”, or something along those lines. Well, it’s good advice, so here it is again. Personally, I’ve made it a rule that I will read for at least 10 minutes every night right before I go to sleep. Not only is this a nice, relaxing way to end the day, but most of the time I end up reading for a fair bit longer anyway - as is often the case, the most important thing is just showing up. The main thing that ties all of these things together is that they all focus on the process of reading, rather than the goal of reading more. In the book Atomic Habits, James Clear gives this advice: If you want better results, then forget about setting goals. Focus on your system instead. Clear argues that the long-term positive behaviour change must rely on systems rather than goals: “You do not rise to the level of your goals. You fall to the level of your systems.” The habits and attitude shifts listed above have meant that I read more in the last few months than I had at any point in the last few years. More importantly, by optimising the reading process and eliminating some of the associated mental blocks, I am able to enjoy the books I read much more, and as a result also get more value out of them. Towards better reading The upshot of all of this is that by eliminating a bunch of the obstacles to reading consistently, then adopting habits that make reading more fun and incorporating them into my daily routine, I have been able to read more, read better, and enjoy it more. Rather than focusing on macroscopic goals like getting through a new book each week, I’ve prioritised simply showing up each day, and creating a system that makes it easy and fun to do so. At any given time, there will be a book on my Kindle that I am keen to read more of, and without the self-imposed pressure to get through it quickly, I can read at a pace that optimises for both enjoyment and value. There are definitely still other avenues I’d like to explore with improving my reading habits. Lots of people swear by audiobooks these days - I personally have tried and enjoyed a handful of them, but mostly tended to prefer podcasts since they are freely available, while audiobooks are a little expensive for my liking. I also hope to experiment with reading some more “challenging” books, in whatever form that might take, with the aim of exploring a little deeper into unfamiliar ideas. For now, though, all of the small habit changes and attitude shifts described in this post have already had a huge cumulative effect on my reading in the last few months, and I’m keen to see where I can take them from here.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breaking the Curse of Expertise</title><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/curse-of-expertise/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking the Curse of Expertise" /><published>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/curse-of-expertise</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/curse-of-expertise/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;That’s all any of us are: amateurs. We don’t live long enough to be anything else.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;Charlie Chaplin&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my second year as an undergraduate, I got a job as a tutor at my university, teaching an introductory programming course. Most of the students in this course were only a year below me academically, and in many cases actually older than me. This was a course that I had done well in the previous year, and felt quite confident that I was well-equipped to teach clearly and intuitively to beginners. However, I found that when I mentioned my teaching job to people, they would often (very tactfully, of course) express their scepticism at the concept of someone tutoring a course that they had taken so recently. In most faculties at my university, undergraduates were not allowed to work as tutors at all, and even in the few where it was allowed, teaching a course the year after taking it was pretty unusual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In part, I understand where these doubts came from - in many fields, teaching effectively on certain topics &lt;em&gt;requires&lt;/em&gt; understanding that goes deeper than the actual content being taught. I found this to be particularly true in my studies of physics, where as first-year students we would often have questions that required significant background knowledge and intuition to answer satisfyingly. However, this is not the case across the board, and certainly wasn’t the case in my course, which was self-contained in such a way that it would not tend to provoke questions that went outside of its scope. In short, if you knew the content and knew how to teach, you would be able to teach it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-curse-of-expertise&quot;&gt;The curse of expertise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our default mindset is to prefer being taught by people whom we consider to be &lt;em&gt;experts&lt;/em&gt;, whatever that might mean in the particular context. We want to learn from people with a lot of &lt;em&gt;experience&lt;/em&gt;, in the hope that we will somehow be able to absorb their distilled knowledge and wisdom - a hope that, at least at first glance, seems completely reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in many cases, expertise can actually be a barrier to effective teaching. C. S. Lewis has a great explanation of this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It often happens that two schoolboys can solve difficulties in their work for one another better than the master can… The fellow-pupil can help more than the master because he knows less. The difficulty we want him to explain is one he has recently met. The expert met it so long ago he has forgotten. He sees the whole subject, by now, in a different light that he cannot conceive what is really troubling the pupil; he sees a dozen other difficulties which ought to be troubling him but aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This phenomenon is today regarded as a cognitive bias called the &lt;em&gt;curse of expertise&lt;/em&gt; (sometimes also called the curse of knowledge). It explains why great practitioners are not always great teachers, and why expertise - although often a reasonable heuristic - should not be what we look for in our teachers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;learning-from-amateurs&quot;&gt;Learning from amateurs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back at the historical picture, it is hard not to hold experts in the highest regard when it comes to teaching. The names whose teachings are passed onto us in school, from Archimedes to Newton to Einstein, are the foremost experts in their fields, whose innovations profoundly advanced our collective knowledge. The people we traditionally learn from directly, the teachers, professors and scholars, got to these roles by first earning recognition as experts from the institutions that publish their work or pay them to teach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The growth of online education represents a major shift away from our reliance on experts for teaching. Today, some of the easiest ways to learn new information or tackle challenging topics are on sites like Khan Academy or Skillshare (not sponsored), educational channels on YouTube, podcasts, blogs, or any number of other corners of the internet. On all of these platforms, there is virtually no requirement for prior expertise, and also little to no startup cost, meaning that the only requirement for acting as a teacher to potentially millions of people is &lt;em&gt;putting out educational content that people like&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expertise as a concept is certainly still valued, but its importance has decreased a lot in the last few years, and will likely continue to do so as the online education space expands. This leaves us in a place where it is easy to &lt;em&gt;overestimate&lt;/em&gt; the expertise of the people whose content we consume. Many of the people we learn from online are not experts, just people who learned a bit about something and were keen to share it with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;you-dont-need-to-be-an-expert&quot;&gt;You don’t need to be an expert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s worth thinking about how these biases towards authority and expertise affect our own behaviour and self-expression. The curse of expertise can actually play into this quite directly - if you become become good at some new skill, for example, it’s easy to forget how hard it was to get there, and effectively become acclimatised to your new ability level. As a result, you underestimate your own knowledge, and the value that you could provide to others as a teacher, thinking that you don’t know enough to be worthy of trying to share your experiences with anyone else. This is closely related to the more well-known concept of &lt;em&gt;impostor syndrome&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/impostor_syndrome_2x.png&quot; style=&quot;width:350px&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Austin Kleon’s book &lt;em&gt;Show Your Work!&lt;/em&gt; aims to break down the barriers that make us reluctant to share our art and ideas with the world, encouraging us to abandon this need to feel like we are &lt;em&gt;qualified&lt;/em&gt; to do so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Forget about being an expert or a professional, and wear your amateurism on your sleeve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a YouTuber named Mike Boyd who I think embodies this sentiment perfectly. In his video series “Learn Quick”, he documents himself trying to learn a difficult skill from scratch as quickly as possible, and in the process provides guidance on how one could follow in his footsteps (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lTYJMke4kd8&quot;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; in which he learns to wheelie his bike for 100 metres non-stop is a particularly good one).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, there is virtually no material barrier to sharing your work or ideas with other people who might be interested in them - the only real barrier is your own willingness to put yourself out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started this blog so that I would have somewhere to write down and share my thoughts whenever I feel like doing so, encouraged to by the various ideas discussed in this post. I hope you found some of it interesting, but don’t take any of it too seriously - I’m not an expert, after all.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Stephens</name><email>stephens@robots.ox.ac.uk</email></author><summary type="html">That’s all any of us are: amateurs. We don’t live long enough to be anything else. Charlie Chaplin In my second year as an undergraduate, I got a job as a tutor at my university, teaching an introductory programming course. Most of the students in this course were only a year below me academically, and in many cases actually older than me. This was a course that I had done well in the previous year, and felt quite confident that I was well-equipped to teach clearly and intuitively to beginners. However, I found that when I mentioned my teaching job to people, they would often (very tactfully, of course) express their scepticism at the concept of someone tutoring a course that they had taken so recently. In most faculties at my university, undergraduates were not allowed to work as tutors at all, and even in the few where it was allowed, teaching a course the year after taking it was pretty unusual. In part, I understand where these doubts came from - in many fields, teaching effectively on certain topics requires understanding that goes deeper than the actual content being taught. I found this to be particularly true in my studies of physics, where as first-year students we would often have questions that required significant background knowledge and intuition to answer satisfyingly. However, this is not the case across the board, and certainly wasn’t the case in my course, which was self-contained in such a way that it would not tend to provoke questions that went outside of its scope. In short, if you knew the content and knew how to teach, you would be able to teach it well. The curse of expertise Our default mindset is to prefer being taught by people whom we consider to be experts, whatever that might mean in the particular context. We want to learn from people with a lot of experience, in the hope that we will somehow be able to absorb their distilled knowledge and wisdom - a hope that, at least at first glance, seems completely reasonable. However, in many cases, expertise can actually be a barrier to effective teaching. C. S. Lewis has a great explanation of this: It often happens that two schoolboys can solve difficulties in their work for one another better than the master can… The fellow-pupil can help more than the master because he knows less. The difficulty we want him to explain is one he has recently met. The expert met it so long ago he has forgotten. He sees the whole subject, by now, in a different light that he cannot conceive what is really troubling the pupil; he sees a dozen other difficulties which ought to be troubling him but aren’t. This phenomenon is today regarded as a cognitive bias called the curse of expertise (sometimes also called the curse of knowledge). It explains why great practitioners are not always great teachers, and why expertise - although often a reasonable heuristic - should not be what we look for in our teachers. Learning from amateurs Looking back at the historical picture, it is hard not to hold experts in the highest regard when it comes to teaching. The names whose teachings are passed onto us in school, from Archimedes to Newton to Einstein, are the foremost experts in their fields, whose innovations profoundly advanced our collective knowledge. The people we traditionally learn from directly, the teachers, professors and scholars, got to these roles by first earning recognition as experts from the institutions that publish their work or pay them to teach. The growth of online education represents a major shift away from our reliance on experts for teaching. Today, some of the easiest ways to learn new information or tackle challenging topics are on sites like Khan Academy or Skillshare (not sponsored), educational channels on YouTube, podcasts, blogs, or any number of other corners of the internet. On all of these platforms, there is virtually no requirement for prior expertise, and also little to no startup cost, meaning that the only requirement for acting as a teacher to potentially millions of people is putting out educational content that people like. Expertise as a concept is certainly still valued, but its importance has decreased a lot in the last few years, and will likely continue to do so as the online education space expands. This leaves us in a place where it is easy to overestimate the expertise of the people whose content we consume. Many of the people we learn from online are not experts, just people who learned a bit about something and were keen to share it with others. You don’t need to be an expert It’s worth thinking about how these biases towards authority and expertise affect our own behaviour and self-expression. The curse of expertise can actually play into this quite directly - if you become become good at some new skill, for example, it’s easy to forget how hard it was to get there, and effectively become acclimatised to your new ability level. As a result, you underestimate your own knowledge, and the value that you could provide to others as a teacher, thinking that you don’t know enough to be worthy of trying to share your experiences with anyone else. This is closely related to the more well-known concept of impostor syndrome. Austin Kleon’s book Show Your Work! aims to break down the barriers that make us reluctant to share our art and ideas with the world, encouraging us to abandon this need to feel like we are qualified to do so: Forget about being an expert or a professional, and wear your amateurism on your sleeve. There’s a YouTuber named Mike Boyd who I think embodies this sentiment perfectly. In his video series “Learn Quick”, he documents himself trying to learn a difficult skill from scratch as quickly as possible, and in the process provides guidance on how one could follow in his footsteps (this video in which he learns to wheelie his bike for 100 metres non-stop is a particularly good one). Today, there is virtually no material barrier to sharing your work or ideas with other people who might be interested in them - the only real barrier is your own willingness to put yourself out there. I started this blog so that I would have somewhere to write down and share my thoughts whenever I feel like doing so, encouraged to by the various ideas discussed in this post. I hope you found some of it interesting, but don’t take any of it too seriously - I’m not an expert, after all.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">`Shift + &amp;gt;` and the Importance of Making It Easy</title><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/make-it-easy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="`Shift + &amp;gt;` and the Importance of Making It Easy" /><published>2020-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/make-it-easy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/make-it-easy/">&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you picked up a new skill or habit that immediately became part of your natural way of doing things?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it was a couple of months ago, when I learned the keyboard shortcut &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;shift + &amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; (or simply &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;) on YouTube, which increases the speed of the current video by one increment (first to 1.25x, then 1.5x, 1.75x, and 2x). Dead easy, and yet this discovery has added a disproportionately huge amount of value to my daily life in the time since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;life-in-the-slow-lane&quot;&gt;Life in the slow lane&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been a big fan of listening to podcasts sped up for quite a while now, since most podcast apps make this easy to do, and it allows me to get through more episodes than I otherwise could. I find that speeding things up a bit actually makes them more engaging and enjoyable to listen to, although the exact speed I opt for depends on the particular podcast. For more information-dense ones, I may find 1x or 1.25x is a comfortable pace, whereas others I can comfortably listen to at 1.75x or 2x. It also depends a bit on what I’m up to while listening - if I’m out on a run, my attention will be almost entirely on the podcast, so I can listen at higher speeds, whereas if I’m cooking or driving my attention might be divided so I’ll opt for slightly slower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I consume plenty of content on YouTube, be it educational, entertainment, or a combination of the two, but until recently I have never regularly adjusted the playback speed on there. The main reason for this is that the user interface makes it pretty cumbersome, requiring three clicks through the menu to change speed once (and then another two if you immediately realise you want to change it again). My preferred playback speed for a given video could be anywhere from 1.25x to 2x, but the effort to adjust it for every video I watched was too much, so I never did it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as I learned the shortcuts (&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;shift + &amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; to increase speed by one increment, &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;shift + &amp;lt;&lt;/code&gt; to slow down), it changed the game almost immediately. Suddenly, it was almost no effort to jump between different speeds and find the fastest comfortable one. No need to distract myself from the video by having to click through the menus - in fact, no need to even glance away from the video while fiddling with the speed. Since discovering this shortcut, I adjust the playback speed on virtually every video I watch, more or less without thinking, and the improvement to my overall YouTube experience has been huge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;make-it-easy&quot;&gt;Make it easy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever ventured into the world of self-help and productivity literature, you’ve probably heard of &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamesclear.com/atomic-habits&quot;&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt; by James Clear, which if you aren’t familiar, is a great practical guide on how habits are built and maintained. In this book, Clear describes what he calls the Four Laws of Behaviour Change, the third of which is “Make It Easy”. It is human nature to prefer actions that require less effort, so by making a habit easier to do, you become more likely to follow through with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optimising my playback speed for videos was something that, on some level, I have wanted to do for a long time. However, that tiny extra effort of three clicks through a menu was enough to deter me from ever actually doing it. As soon as it became a single two-button keyboard shortcut, it became a habit that I am virtually guaranteed to continue with for the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So take the a couple of minutes to flick through the keyboard shortcuts for programs (or, in this case, websites) that you spend a lot of time on, and try some of them out. Most of them probably won’t stick, but those few that you do end up using constantly are the ones that make all the difference.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Stephens</name><email>stephens@robots.ox.ac.uk</email></author><summary type="html">When was the last time you picked up a new skill or habit that immediately became part of your natural way of doing things? For me, it was a couple of months ago, when I learned the keyboard shortcut shift + &amp;gt; (or simply &amp;gt;) on YouTube, which increases the speed of the current video by one increment (first to 1.25x, then 1.5x, 1.75x, and 2x). Dead easy, and yet this discovery has added a disproportionately huge amount of value to my daily life in the time since. Life in the slow lane I’ve been a big fan of listening to podcasts sped up for quite a while now, since most podcast apps make this easy to do, and it allows me to get through more episodes than I otherwise could. I find that speeding things up a bit actually makes them more engaging and enjoyable to listen to, although the exact speed I opt for depends on the particular podcast. For more information-dense ones, I may find 1x or 1.25x is a comfortable pace, whereas others I can comfortably listen to at 1.75x or 2x. It also depends a bit on what I’m up to while listening - if I’m out on a run, my attention will be almost entirely on the podcast, so I can listen at higher speeds, whereas if I’m cooking or driving my attention might be divided so I’ll opt for slightly slower. I consume plenty of content on YouTube, be it educational, entertainment, or a combination of the two, but until recently I have never regularly adjusted the playback speed on there. The main reason for this is that the user interface makes it pretty cumbersome, requiring three clicks through the menu to change speed once (and then another two if you immediately realise you want to change it again). My preferred playback speed for a given video could be anywhere from 1.25x to 2x, but the effort to adjust it for every video I watched was too much, so I never did it. As soon as I learned the shortcuts (shift + &amp;gt; to increase speed by one increment, shift + &amp;lt; to slow down), it changed the game almost immediately. Suddenly, it was almost no effort to jump between different speeds and find the fastest comfortable one. No need to distract myself from the video by having to click through the menus - in fact, no need to even glance away from the video while fiddling with the speed. Since discovering this shortcut, I adjust the playback speed on virtually every video I watch, more or less without thinking, and the improvement to my overall YouTube experience has been huge. Make it easy If you’ve ever ventured into the world of self-help and productivity literature, you’ve probably heard of Atomic Habits by James Clear, which if you aren’t familiar, is a great practical guide on how habits are built and maintained. In this book, Clear describes what he calls the Four Laws of Behaviour Change, the third of which is “Make It Easy”. It is human nature to prefer actions that require less effort, so by making a habit easier to do, you become more likely to follow through with it. Optimising my playback speed for videos was something that, on some level, I have wanted to do for a long time. However, that tiny extra effort of three clicks through a menu was enough to deter me from ever actually doing it. As soon as it became a single two-button keyboard shortcut, it became a habit that I am virtually guaranteed to continue with for the foreseeable future. So take the a couple of minutes to flick through the keyboard shortcuts for programs (or, in this case, websites) that you spend a lot of time on, and try some of them out. Most of them probably won’t stick, but those few that you do end up using constantly are the ones that make all the difference.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Rule of Six</title><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/rule-of-six/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Rule of Six" /><published>2020-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-18T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/rule-of-six</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/rule-of-six/">&lt;p&gt;About a month ago, I moved from Australia to the UK to start a PhD at the University of Oxford. While I was quite excited for the move despite the uncertainty of relocating halfway around the world during a global pandemic, I still arrived with the expectation that I would not be able to have the usual social experience of a new student (a &lt;em&gt;fresher&lt;/em&gt;, if you will) at Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the hallmarks of this experience is Freshers’ Week, the week before the academic year starts, during which the colleges (one of which every student at Oxford is a member of) run the gamut of social events that you might expect for a bunch of uni students who want to make new friends - which is to say, a lot of drinking events, and a couple of other events that will probably end up involving alcohol at some point too. In my case, the events were organised by the graduate student committee of Exeter College, catering to the 100 or so graduate students joining the college for the 2020-21 academic year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-rule-of-six&quot;&gt;The rule of six&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year, all of these events had to be organised in accordance with the UK Government health guidelines, most notably the  dramatically named “rule of six”. As the name implies, this rule restricts all social gatherings to a maximum of six people in any setting - indoors, outdoors, public venues, private accommodation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rule of six meant that the Freshers’ Week events this year looked quite different than usual. Where there might previously have been rowdy parties, pub nights, or big outdoor evemts, we now faced a series of events that were all carefully planned to comply with guidelines. Pre-registration became essential, and any events at pubs or restaurants were limited to bookings of 6 with strictly communication between tables. Some events were designed around “household” groups, the small groups of students sharing living spaces at the college accommodation complex, who were considered to form a social bubble within which COVID transmission was an accepted risk. The result was that all of the events essentially involved hanging out with the same small group of people for an entire afternoon or evening, with no mixing whatsoever with other groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, the point of this post is not to complain about any of this - in fact quite the opposite. These rules are obviously important, and the Exeter fresher cohort was extremely grateful that the committee went to the considerable effort of planning out all of these events for us under the challenging circumstances. The freshers at some of the other Oxford colleges weren’t so lucky, and essentially missed out on the Freshers’ Week social experience altogether.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually came out of Freshers’ Week feeling that I’d made plenty of friends and generally had an excellent time at all of the events, despite some misgivings from before it all got started. However, this was initially tinged with the understanding that it could have been &lt;em&gt;even better&lt;/em&gt; in the absence of the pandemic, and that we’d somehow missed out on the “full experience”… But the more I thought about it in the days after, the more I realised that actually although some of the events might not have been as superficially exciting this year, they were actually a &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; experience for connecting with new people and making friends, which is exactly the point of Freshers’ Week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-optionality&quot;&gt;Social optionality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand how I came to the conclusion that the rule of six restriction improved my experience of Freshers’ Week, let’s take a quick look at the idea of &lt;em&gt;social optionality&lt;/em&gt;. I came across this concept in an episode of the podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://notoverthinking.com/&quot;&gt;Not Overthinking&lt;/a&gt;, in which one of the hosts, Taimur Abdaal, introduces the idea as a way of thinking about how we approach social interactions. He has a great blog post about it which you can check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://taimur.me/posts/against-social-optionality/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if you’re interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The social optionality of an event or situation refers to how easy it is to engage or disengage with social interactions. An example of a high social optionality situation might be a networking event or a large party, where everyone is meeting new people, and it’s generally pretty easy to eject yourself from a conversation and move onto another one if you don’t feel like you’re hitting it off with someone. At the other end of the scale, an example Taimur uses of a low optionality event is a group holiday, where a group of, say, 8 people go somewhere for a couple of days, and are basically committed to engaging socially with each other for this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the key ideas that Taimur presents about this is that the social optionality of a situation significantly changes how we approach it. In a very high optionality scenario, we are constantly - either consciously or subconsciously - evaluating new people we interact with - we are thinking, am I getting along with this person? Is this the kind of person I want to become better friends with? If we’re not convinced, it’s easy to just move on and find someone else to talk to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In low optionality events, this mindset doesn’t work any more - we know that we &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; to interact with the people around us, so we instead start thinking about &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to connect with them. We throw away our superficial judgements, and look for common ground upon which to build a connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Wanting to connect for no other reason than because you’re two human beings on the same floating rock — this is the intention with which I’d like to approach all social interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taimur concludes that the high optionality mindset causes us to miss out on making meaningful connections because we more ready to dismiss people instead of putting in the effort, and that ideally we should approach all interactions with something akin to the low optionality mindset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-unexpected-result&quot;&gt;The unexpected result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusion I came to is that the effect of the UK Government’s social gathering restrictions on Freshers’ Week experience at Exeter College was precisely to &lt;em&gt;lower the social optionality of all of the events&lt;/em&gt;. Had Freshers’ Week involved, for example, the big wine and cheese night that is sometimes on the agenda, I have no doubt that I would have had a great time, and probably chatted with loads of new people in the space of a few short hours. However, it’s likely that many of these conversations would have been that typical awkward small talk that sometimes dominates events where nobody knows each other, and I probably would’ve forgotten the names of many of the people I met by the following morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, at pretty much all events I attended, I spoke for at least couple of hours with the same four or five people. While this might seem superficially less exciting than the wine and cheese night, I found that the conversations I did have were far better than what I would typically expect from talking to a group of people I’d just met and didn’t necessarily have much in common with besides the university we attend. By the end of Freshers’ Week, I found that I had a whole lot of small groups of new friends from these events, each of which will now happily continue to meet up (in a socially responsible manner, of course), often with someone bringing along a new person or two to introduce to the rest if capacity allows. Since &lt;em&gt;every event&lt;/em&gt; involved only a few people, I felt that I was able to connect better with new people, have more interesting conversations, and become closer than would otherwise have been possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, strange as it might seem, for this one week that kicked off my new life as a PhD student in a foreign country, the government restrictions on social gatherings actually &lt;em&gt;improved&lt;/em&gt; my social experience significantly. The social events, adapting to the challenging circumstances, turned into lower optionality settings which - although perhaps superficially less exciting at times - were genuinely more valuable because of it.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Stephens</name><email>stephens@robots.ox.ac.uk</email></author><summary type="html">About a month ago, I moved from Australia to the UK to start a PhD at the University of Oxford. While I was quite excited for the move despite the uncertainty of relocating halfway around the world during a global pandemic, I still arrived with the expectation that I would not be able to have the usual social experience of a new student (a fresher, if you will) at Oxford. One of the hallmarks of this experience is Freshers’ Week, the week before the academic year starts, during which the colleges (one of which every student at Oxford is a member of) run the gamut of social events that you might expect for a bunch of uni students who want to make new friends - which is to say, a lot of drinking events, and a couple of other events that will probably end up involving alcohol at some point too. In my case, the events were organised by the graduate student committee of Exeter College, catering to the 100 or so graduate students joining the college for the 2020-21 academic year. The rule of six This year, all of these events had to be organised in accordance with the UK Government health guidelines, most notably the dramatically named “rule of six”. As the name implies, this rule restricts all social gatherings to a maximum of six people in any setting - indoors, outdoors, public venues, private accommodation. The rule of six meant that the Freshers’ Week events this year looked quite different than usual. Where there might previously have been rowdy parties, pub nights, or big outdoor evemts, we now faced a series of events that were all carefully planned to comply with guidelines. Pre-registration became essential, and any events at pubs or restaurants were limited to bookings of 6 with strictly communication between tables. Some events were designed around “household” groups, the small groups of students sharing living spaces at the college accommodation complex, who were considered to form a social bubble within which COVID transmission was an accepted risk. The result was that all of the events essentially involved hanging out with the same small group of people for an entire afternoon or evening, with no mixing whatsoever with other groups. Don’t get me wrong, the point of this post is not to complain about any of this - in fact quite the opposite. These rules are obviously important, and the Exeter fresher cohort was extremely grateful that the committee went to the considerable effort of planning out all of these events for us under the challenging circumstances. The freshers at some of the other Oxford colleges weren’t so lucky, and essentially missed out on the Freshers’ Week social experience altogether. I actually came out of Freshers’ Week feeling that I’d made plenty of friends and generally had an excellent time at all of the events, despite some misgivings from before it all got started. However, this was initially tinged with the understanding that it could have been even better in the absence of the pandemic, and that we’d somehow missed out on the “full experience”… But the more I thought about it in the days after, the more I realised that actually although some of the events might not have been as superficially exciting this year, they were actually a better experience for connecting with new people and making friends, which is exactly the point of Freshers’ Week. Social optionality To understand how I came to the conclusion that the rule of six restriction improved my experience of Freshers’ Week, let’s take a quick look at the idea of social optionality. I came across this concept in an episode of the podcast Not Overthinking, in which one of the hosts, Taimur Abdaal, introduces the idea as a way of thinking about how we approach social interactions. He has a great blog post about it which you can check out here if you’re interested. The social optionality of an event or situation refers to how easy it is to engage or disengage with social interactions. An example of a high social optionality situation might be a networking event or a large party, where everyone is meeting new people, and it’s generally pretty easy to eject yourself from a conversation and move onto another one if you don’t feel like you’re hitting it off with someone. At the other end of the scale, an example Taimur uses of a low optionality event is a group holiday, where a group of, say, 8 people go somewhere for a couple of days, and are basically committed to engaging socially with each other for this time. One of the key ideas that Taimur presents about this is that the social optionality of a situation significantly changes how we approach it. In a very high optionality scenario, we are constantly - either consciously or subconsciously - evaluating new people we interact with - we are thinking, am I getting along with this person? Is this the kind of person I want to become better friends with? If we’re not convinced, it’s easy to just move on and find someone else to talk to. In low optionality events, this mindset doesn’t work any more - we know that we have to interact with the people around us, so we instead start thinking about how to connect with them. We throw away our superficial judgements, and look for common ground upon which to build a connection. Wanting to connect for no other reason than because you’re two human beings on the same floating rock — this is the intention with which I’d like to approach all social interactions. Taimur concludes that the high optionality mindset causes us to miss out on making meaningful connections because we more ready to dismiss people instead of putting in the effort, and that ideally we should approach all interactions with something akin to the low optionality mindset. The unexpected result The conclusion I came to is that the effect of the UK Government’s social gathering restrictions on Freshers’ Week experience at Exeter College was precisely to lower the social optionality of all of the events. Had Freshers’ Week involved, for example, the big wine and cheese night that is sometimes on the agenda, I have no doubt that I would have had a great time, and probably chatted with loads of new people in the space of a few short hours. However, it’s likely that many of these conversations would have been that typical awkward small talk that sometimes dominates events where nobody knows each other, and I probably would’ve forgotten the names of many of the people I met by the following morning. Instead, at pretty much all events I attended, I spoke for at least couple of hours with the same four or five people. While this might seem superficially less exciting than the wine and cheese night, I found that the conversations I did have were far better than what I would typically expect from talking to a group of people I’d just met and didn’t necessarily have much in common with besides the university we attend. By the end of Freshers’ Week, I found that I had a whole lot of small groups of new friends from these events, each of which will now happily continue to meet up (in a socially responsible manner, of course), often with someone bringing along a new person or two to introduce to the rest if capacity allows. Since every event involved only a few people, I felt that I was able to connect better with new people, have more interesting conversations, and become closer than would otherwise have been possible. So, strange as it might seem, for this one week that kicked off my new life as a PhD student in a foreign country, the government restrictions on social gatherings actually improved my social experience significantly. The social events, adapting to the challenging circumstances, turned into lower optionality settings which - although perhaps superficially less exciting at times - were genuinely more valuable because of it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Demon Haunted World of COVID-19</title><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/demon-haunted-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Demon Haunted World of COVID-19" /><published>2020-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/demon-haunted-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/demon-haunted-world/">&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, I came across a quote that has been circulating online a fair bit this year. The quote comes from the 1995 book &lt;em&gt;The Demon Haunted World&lt;/em&gt; by the American astrophysicist and science communicator Carl Sagan, and reads as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I have a foreboding of an America in my children’s or grandchildren’s time – when the United States is a service and information economy; when nearly all the manufacturing industries have slipped away to other countries; when awesome technological powers are in the hands of a very few, and no one representing the public interest can even grasp the issues; when the people have lost the ability to set their own agendas or knowledgeably question those in authority; when, clutching our crystals and nervously consulting our horoscopes, our critical faculties in decline, unable to distinguish between what feels good and what’s true, we slide, almost without noticing, back into superstition and darkness…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This passage, particularly the final third, resonated quite strongly with me because I felt that despite having been published 25 years ago, it hints at some of the greatest issues facing our the pandemic-stricken world today. Throughout the COVID-19 pandemic this year, I have been surprised on many occasions by the number of people who have seemed willing to ideologically reject scientific advice. How is it that in 2020, when our collective scientific understanding is the most developed and accessible that it has ever been, that well-established science can still be reduced to a matter of opinion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June, Dr Anthony Fauci, one of top infectious disease experts and health advisors in the US, lamented the “anti-science bias” present in the country, attributing the country’s ineffective pandemic response to this bias. Be it refusal to wear face masks in public, or denial of the existence of the virus altogether, anti-scientific attitudes have run rampant this year. My first thought upon reading the above quote was that Sagan, who died in 1996, would not have been surprised by this. I wondered if the book might help me to better understand our collective response to the coronavirus pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;preferring-the-darkness&quot;&gt;Preferring the darkness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full title of Sagan’s book is &lt;em&gt;The Demon-Haunted World: Science as a Candle in the Dark&lt;/em&gt;. The subtitle is a reference to the 1656 book &lt;em&gt;A Candle in the Dark&lt;/em&gt; by Thomas Ady, a sceptical attack on the then-popular practice of witch-hunting. Witches were persecuted for their supposed supernatural abilities, used as scapegoats for various misfortunes, and frequently forced by torture to confess to various crimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ady describes the witch mania as a scam “to delude the people”, arguing against the interpretations of the Bible that were frequently used to justify witch-hunting. Quoting a justification given by witchmongers for the existence of witches, Ady writes, “witches must exist, else how should these things be, or come to pass?” The popular mindset in England during Ady’s time was strongly determined by religious leaders, and their conclusions were rarely questioned so directly. In an era in which people were fearful of the outside world, they turned readily to anywhere that would explain away their terrors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sagan draws parallels between the witch mania and the alien abduction phenomenon of the later 20th century. He points out that although the entire concept could be explained away by fairly basic lines of questioning, many people claimed nonetheless to have been abducted by aliens, and many more believed these stories. The common traits of the supposed aliens were particularly telling – in different cultures’ representations of them, they always bore strong resemblance to humans. People who claimed to have communicated with aliens would never learn any interesting information from them (new scientific knowledge or answers to unsolved mathematical problems, for example) only vague statements about the meaning of life that could easily have been conjured up by an attention seeker. Their warnings for the future always centred on well-known fears (e.g. that of nuclear war in the 1950s), never demonstrating any convincing foreknowledge. The concept of alien abduction did not hold up to basic scepticism, and yet people &lt;em&gt;wanted&lt;/em&gt; to believe in aliens, so they did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;additional-driving-forces&quot;&gt;Additional driving forces&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of societal upheaval, the fact that we tend to prefer to hold onto our existing worldview is not particularly surprising. There is little to enjoy about any of the widespread behaviour changes demanded by COVID, and many have led to significant hardships for large portions of the population. In the US and many other countries, this tendency is compounded by the poor standard of scientific education, which contributes to a society in which people do not think critically about the information they are presented. As soon as an anti-scientific movement gains a little steam, it is readily adopted by the large cross-section of society who see it as a preferable alternative to accepting the reality of the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, I feel like these two key points – our natural preference for preserving existing worldviews, compounded by a lack of education in scepticism and critical thought – go a decent way towards explaining the anti-science bias present in much of the world today. However, I would say that there is a third element which is also an essential part of the picture, and that is the presence of &lt;em&gt;direct incentives to go against science,&lt;/em&gt; which exist at all levels of society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The countries whose COVID-19 responses I have followed most closely are Australia – where I was living for the first few months of the pandemic – as well as the United States and several European countries, due largely to their prominence in media coverage. Many of these are strongly capitalistic societies, in which many motives that run counter to public health advice have been very clearly on display in the last few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sagan’s book discusses a couple of examples of similar phenomena in recent history – it is worth looking at one of these in a bit of depth to see some parallels with what is happening now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;smoke-and-mirrors&quot;&gt;Smoke and mirrors&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 1960s, it is estimated that over 40% of Americans were regular smokers, a number that plummeted in the subsequent decades. This was largely due to a variety of scientific studies conducted in the 1950s and 1960s that demonstrated causal links between smoking and a variety of adverse health effects. However, the attitude shift in the medical community was slow, and is thought to have been hindered by resistance from nicotine-dependent doctors who were reluctant to believe in the dangers of smoking. The tobacco industry used its considerable influence to suppress scientific studies and lobby against tobacco controls that came under consideration as a result of these studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sagan’s book references a 1971 internal report from the Brown and Williamson Tobacco Corporation, claiming that the industry was a victim of unsupported claims drawing false links to lung cancer and calling this the “greatest libel and slander ever perpetrated against any product in the history of free enterprise”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, this strikes a chord with what we see today - powerful, profit-driven entities digging their heels in to prevent the acceptance of ideas that will inevitably be financially damaging. Incentives to go against health advice are present at all levels in capitalist society, from the industrial CEO who wants to avoid a lockdown so that their factories can remain productive, to the working adult who cannot afford to two weeks of work for self-isolation even when they show symptoms of COVID. These sentiments are propagated through the media we consume, leaving people in a position where they can choose a narrative that suits them best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A point that is worth clarifying here is that these incentives only directly encourage us to &lt;em&gt;act&lt;/em&gt; against the scientific advice, not necessarily to actually disbelieve it  – a completely rational person could understand the dangers of the virus and yet go to work anyway because they need to earn money to support their family. Somewhat similarly, many people smoke cigarettes because they enjoy doing so, even if they understand the long-term health risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, at a certain point, it becomes tempting to start to self-justify, and to actually &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; that what we are doing is unequivocally right – we would rather not think about the compromises we have made. This is expressed by Sagan as a trend seen throughout history:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One of the saddest lessons of history is this: if we’ve been bamboozled long enough, we tend to reject any evidence of the bamboozle. We’re no longer interested in finding out the truth. The bamboozle has captured us. It’s simply too painful to acknowledge, even to ourselves, that we’ve been taken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This acts as a first step in disconnecting ourselves from reality, by choosing to believe something that we once knew on a rational level to be false. We must be willing to critically examine our own beliefs and the foundations upon which they are built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-path-forwards&quot;&gt;The path forwards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main idea that was driven home for me by Sagan’s book is that any society that is not well-educated in critical thought and scepticism is one that will readily slide into superstition and darkness. Our willingness to accept information that changes our view of the world competes with our natural resistance to change, a balance that can be tipped further against science by societal pressures. By actively examining our own beliefs, and questioning the assumptions and motives behind the information that is presented to us, perhaps we can work towards tipping the balance back the other way.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Stephens</name><email>stephens@robots.ox.ac.uk</email></author><summary type="html">A couple of months ago, I came across a quote that has been circulating online a fair bit this year. The quote comes from the 1995 book The Demon Haunted World by the American astrophysicist and science communicator Carl Sagan, and reads as follows: I have a foreboding of an America in my children’s or grandchildren’s time – when the United States is a service and information economy; when nearly all the manufacturing industries have slipped away to other countries; when awesome technological powers are in the hands of a very few, and no one representing the public interest can even grasp the issues; when the people have lost the ability to set their own agendas or knowledgeably question those in authority; when, clutching our crystals and nervously consulting our horoscopes, our critical faculties in decline, unable to distinguish between what feels good and what’s true, we slide, almost without noticing, back into superstition and darkness… This passage, particularly the final third, resonated quite strongly with me because I felt that despite having been published 25 years ago, it hints at some of the greatest issues facing our the pandemic-stricken world today. Throughout the COVID-19 pandemic this year, I have been surprised on many occasions by the number of people who have seemed willing to ideologically reject scientific advice. How is it that in 2020, when our collective scientific understanding is the most developed and accessible that it has ever been, that well-established science can still be reduced to a matter of opinion? In June, Dr Anthony Fauci, one of top infectious disease experts and health advisors in the US, lamented the “anti-science bias” present in the country, attributing the country’s ineffective pandemic response to this bias. Be it refusal to wear face masks in public, or denial of the existence of the virus altogether, anti-scientific attitudes have run rampant this year. My first thought upon reading the above quote was that Sagan, who died in 1996, would not have been surprised by this. I wondered if the book might help me to better understand our collective response to the coronavirus pandemic. Preferring the darkness The full title of Sagan’s book is The Demon-Haunted World: Science as a Candle in the Dark. The subtitle is a reference to the 1656 book A Candle in the Dark by Thomas Ady, a sceptical attack on the then-popular practice of witch-hunting. Witches were persecuted for their supposed supernatural abilities, used as scapegoats for various misfortunes, and frequently forced by torture to confess to various crimes. Ady describes the witch mania as a scam “to delude the people”, arguing against the interpretations of the Bible that were frequently used to justify witch-hunting. Quoting a justification given by witchmongers for the existence of witches, Ady writes, “witches must exist, else how should these things be, or come to pass?” The popular mindset in England during Ady’s time was strongly determined by religious leaders, and their conclusions were rarely questioned so directly. In an era in which people were fearful of the outside world, they turned readily to anywhere that would explain away their terrors. Sagan draws parallels between the witch mania and the alien abduction phenomenon of the later 20th century. He points out that although the entire concept could be explained away by fairly basic lines of questioning, many people claimed nonetheless to have been abducted by aliens, and many more believed these stories. The common traits of the supposed aliens were particularly telling – in different cultures’ representations of them, they always bore strong resemblance to humans. People who claimed to have communicated with aliens would never learn any interesting information from them (new scientific knowledge or answers to unsolved mathematical problems, for example) only vague statements about the meaning of life that could easily have been conjured up by an attention seeker. Their warnings for the future always centred on well-known fears (e.g. that of nuclear war in the 1950s), never demonstrating any convincing foreknowledge. The concept of alien abduction did not hold up to basic scepticism, and yet people wanted to believe in aliens, so they did. Additional driving forces In the face of societal upheaval, the fact that we tend to prefer to hold onto our existing worldview is not particularly surprising. There is little to enjoy about any of the widespread behaviour changes demanded by COVID, and many have led to significant hardships for large portions of the population. In the US and many other countries, this tendency is compounded by the poor standard of scientific education, which contributes to a society in which people do not think critically about the information they are presented. As soon as an anti-scientific movement gains a little steam, it is readily adopted by the large cross-section of society who see it as a preferable alternative to accepting the reality of the pandemic. At this point, I feel like these two key points – our natural preference for preserving existing worldviews, compounded by a lack of education in scepticism and critical thought – go a decent way towards explaining the anti-science bias present in much of the world today. However, I would say that there is a third element which is also an essential part of the picture, and that is the presence of direct incentives to go against science, which exist at all levels of society. The countries whose COVID-19 responses I have followed most closely are Australia – where I was living for the first few months of the pandemic – as well as the United States and several European countries, due largely to their prominence in media coverage. Many of these are strongly capitalistic societies, in which many motives that run counter to public health advice have been very clearly on display in the last few months. Sagan’s book discusses a couple of examples of similar phenomena in recent history – it is worth looking at one of these in a bit of depth to see some parallels with what is happening now. Smoke and mirrors In the 1960s, it is estimated that over 40% of Americans were regular smokers, a number that plummeted in the subsequent decades. This was largely due to a variety of scientific studies conducted in the 1950s and 1960s that demonstrated causal links between smoking and a variety of adverse health effects. However, the attitude shift in the medical community was slow, and is thought to have been hindered by resistance from nicotine-dependent doctors who were reluctant to believe in the dangers of smoking. The tobacco industry used its considerable influence to suppress scientific studies and lobby against tobacco controls that came under consideration as a result of these studies. Sagan’s book references a 1971 internal report from the Brown and Williamson Tobacco Corporation, claiming that the industry was a victim of unsupported claims drawing false links to lung cancer and calling this the “greatest libel and slander ever perpetrated against any product in the history of free enterprise”. To me, this strikes a chord with what we see today - powerful, profit-driven entities digging their heels in to prevent the acceptance of ideas that will inevitably be financially damaging. Incentives to go against health advice are present at all levels in capitalist society, from the industrial CEO who wants to avoid a lockdown so that their factories can remain productive, to the working adult who cannot afford to two weeks of work for self-isolation even when they show symptoms of COVID. These sentiments are propagated through the media we consume, leaving people in a position where they can choose a narrative that suits them best. A point that is worth clarifying here is that these incentives only directly encourage us to act against the scientific advice, not necessarily to actually disbelieve it – a completely rational person could understand the dangers of the virus and yet go to work anyway because they need to earn money to support their family. Somewhat similarly, many people smoke cigarettes because they enjoy doing so, even if they understand the long-term health risks. However, at a certain point, it becomes tempting to start to self-justify, and to actually believe that what we are doing is unequivocally right – we would rather not think about the compromises we have made. This is expressed by Sagan as a trend seen throughout history: One of the saddest lessons of history is this: if we’ve been bamboozled long enough, we tend to reject any evidence of the bamboozle. We’re no longer interested in finding out the truth. The bamboozle has captured us. It’s simply too painful to acknowledge, even to ourselves, that we’ve been taken. This acts as a first step in disconnecting ourselves from reality, by choosing to believe something that we once knew on a rational level to be false. We must be willing to critically examine our own beliefs and the foundations upon which they are built. The path forwards The main idea that was driven home for me by Sagan’s book is that any society that is not well-educated in critical thought and scepticism is one that will readily slide into superstition and darkness. Our willingness to accept information that changes our view of the world competes with our natural resistance to change, a balance that can be tipped further against science by societal pressures. By actively examining our own beliefs, and questioning the assumptions and motives behind the information that is presented to us, perhaps we can work towards tipping the balance back the other way.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Generative Art</title><link href="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/generative/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Generative Art" /><published>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/generative</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://alex-stephens.github.io/blog/generative/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-generative-art&quot;&gt;What is generative art?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Generative art refers to any art practice where the artist uses a system, such
as a set of natural language rules, a computer program, a machine, or other
procedural invention, which is set into motion with some degree of autonomy
contributing to or resulting in a completed work of art.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/summary?doi=10.1.1.90.2634&quot;&gt;Philip Galanter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/cite&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since first learning of the concept of generative art, I have been intrigued by what it has to offer. The idea of creating art with computer programs in particular caught my interest, since this is a medium that is both familiar and accessible to me. Experimenting with it myself, with the help of a variety of online resources, revealed the rich possibilities of creating visually satisfying artworks from foundations of algorithms and mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of generating art programmatically typically involves randomness and tuneable parameters, making it highly dynamic and iterative. As I experimented I found I was often surprised by the results that came from changing parameters in my code, leading me to ideas that were not part of my original vision. Equally fun is looking at other peoples’ generated artworks, and trying to deduce what algorithms or mathematical concepts might have been used to create them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are plenty of resources online that explain in more detail what generative art really is, and the many different tools and techniques that are used to create it, so these aspects won’t be the focus here (although if you are interested in a broader introduction to generative art, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.artnome.com/news/2018/8/8/why-love-generative-art&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; is excellent). The aim of this post is to demonstrate how an extremely simple base element or idea can be iterated upon to generate patterns that are (in my opinion, at least) surprisingly complex and pleasing to the eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;generating-a-simple-pattern&quot;&gt;Generating a simple pattern&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start off, let’s have a look at an example of a generative art pattern, which I created using the Javascript library &lt;a href=&quot;https://p5js.org/&quot;&gt;p5.js&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;bordered&quot; src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/basic.png&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looks pretty nice, right? Take a minute to look carefully at the image above, and think about this key question - &lt;strong&gt;how would you recreate the pattern?&lt;/strong&gt; We want to come up with a &lt;em&gt;plain English description&lt;/em&gt; of how one could go about producing something that looks like this. Can you come up with a simple process that would achieve this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is probably a lot simpler than you’re thinking - the solutions that I went to at first were definitely unnecessarily complex. In fact, all you need to construct the pattern is the two tiles shown below, each consisting of a pair of opposing quarter circles. They’re really the same tile, just with a 90 degree rotational offset between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;bordered&quot; src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/tile-1.png&quot; width=&quot;25%&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;bordered&quot; src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/tile-2.png&quot; width=&quot;25%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make this a bit clearer, here’s the original pattern again, this time with the tiles outlined:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img class=&quot;bordered&quot; src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/basic-outline.png&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first saw this, which is an example of something called a &lt;em&gt;Truchet pattern&lt;/em&gt;, I was pretty amazed by how simple it was to create. I was intrigued by the fact that it was not obvious from looking at the pattern how one would go about reproducing it, and yet once I found out the solution it was suddenly so simple. This, I think, is important in many types of generative art - the underlying ideas are often not as complex as they might seem at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;developing-the-pattern&quot;&gt;Developing the pattern&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what else can we do with this type of pattern? One way to extend the design is by layering the pattern at multiple scales, using different shades and line thicknesses to create aesthetic variation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;carouselTruchetBW&quot; class=&quot;carousel slide carousel-fade&quot; data-ride=&quot;carousel&quot; data-interval=&quot;1500&quot;&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-inner&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-item active&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img class=&quot;bordered&quot; src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/bw-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Base pattern&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-item&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img class=&quot;bordered&quot; src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/bw-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Second layer&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-item&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img class=&quot;bordered&quot; src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/bw-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Third layer&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;a class=&quot;carousel-control-prev&quot; href=&quot;#carouselTruchetBW&quot; role=&quot;button&quot; data-slide=&quot;prev&quot;&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;carousel-control-prev-icon&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;sr-only&quot;&gt;Previous&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;a class=&quot;carousel-control-next&quot; href=&quot;#carouselTruchetBW&quot; role=&quot;button&quot; data-slide=&quot;next&quot;&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;carousel-control-next-icon&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;sr-only&quot;&gt;Next&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;

    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the beauty of generating art from code is that once the base program is written, modifications of this type (scaling, layering, etc.) are quick and easy. This is part of why the genre lends itself so well to experimentation, either manually or through randomisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, let’s add some colour. Shown below are a few more layered Truchet patterns, created with somewhat randomised sizes and scales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;middle&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div id=&quot;carouselTruchetColored&quot; class=&quot;carousel slide carousel-fade&quot; data-ride=&quot;carousel&quot; data-interval=&quot;2500&quot;&gt;

      &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-inner&quot;&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-item active&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img class=&quot;bordered&quot; src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/colored-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pattern 1&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-item&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img class=&quot;bordered&quot; src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/colored-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pattern 2&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-item&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img class=&quot;bordered&quot; src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/colored-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pattern 3&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
        &lt;div class=&quot;carousel-item&quot;&gt;
          &lt;img class=&quot;bordered&quot; src=&quot;/assets/2020-09-01-generative/colored-4.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pattern 4&quot; /&gt;
        &lt;/div&gt;
      &lt;/div&gt;

      &lt;a class=&quot;carousel-control-prev&quot; href=&quot;#carouselTruchetColored&quot; role=&quot;button&quot; data-slide=&quot;prev&quot;&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;carousel-control-prev-icon&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;sr-only&quot;&gt;Previous&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;a class=&quot;carousel-control-next&quot; href=&quot;#carouselTruchetColored&quot; role=&quot;button&quot; data-slide=&quot;next&quot;&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;carousel-control-next-icon&quot; aria-hidden=&quot;true&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;sr-only&quot;&gt;Next&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The addition of colour not only makes the patterns much more interesting to look at, but differentiates them even further from each other, taking us further and further from the basic tiles we started with. The beauty and complexity of the final artwork disguises the simplicity of the building blocks - a statement that is true of the simple patterns seen in this post, but also, I think, of generative art as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Alex Stephens</name><email>stephens@robots.ox.ac.uk</email></author><summary type="html">What is generative art? Generative art refers to any art practice where the artist uses a system, such as a set of natural language rules, a computer program, a machine, or other procedural invention, which is set into motion with some degree of autonomy contributing to or resulting in a completed work of art. Philip Galanter Since first learning of the concept of generative art, I have been intrigued by what it has to offer. The idea of creating art with computer programs in particular caught my interest, since this is a medium that is both familiar and accessible to me. Experimenting with it myself, with the help of a variety of online resources, revealed the rich possibilities of creating visually satisfying artworks from foundations of algorithms and mathematics. The process of generating art programmatically typically involves randomness and tuneable parameters, making it highly dynamic and iterative. As I experimented I found I was often surprised by the results that came from changing parameters in my code, leading me to ideas that were not part of my original vision. Equally fun is looking at other peoples’ generated artworks, and trying to deduce what algorithms or mathematical concepts might have been used to create them. There are plenty of resources online that explain in more detail what generative art really is, and the many different tools and techniques that are used to create it, so these aspects won’t be the focus here (although if you are interested in a broader introduction to generative art, this article is excellent). The aim of this post is to demonstrate how an extremely simple base element or idea can be iterated upon to generate patterns that are (in my opinion, at least) surprisingly complex and pleasing to the eye. Generating a simple pattern To start off, let’s have a look at an example of a generative art pattern, which I created using the Javascript library p5.js. Looks pretty nice, right? Take a minute to look carefully at the image above, and think about this key question - how would you recreate the pattern? We want to come up with a plain English description of how one could go about producing something that looks like this. Can you come up with a simple process that would achieve this? The solution is probably a lot simpler than you’re thinking - the solutions that I went to at first were definitely unnecessarily complex. In fact, all you need to construct the pattern is the two tiles shown below, each consisting of a pair of opposing quarter circles. They’re really the same tile, just with a 90 degree rotational offset between them. To make this a bit clearer, here’s the original pattern again, this time with the tiles outlined: When I first saw this, which is an example of something called a Truchet pattern, I was pretty amazed by how simple it was to create. I was intrigued by the fact that it was not obvious from looking at the pattern how one would go about reproducing it, and yet once I found out the solution it was suddenly so simple. This, I think, is important in many types of generative art - the underlying ideas are often not as complex as they might seem at first. Developing the pattern So what else can we do with this type of pattern? One way to extend the design is by layering the pattern at multiple scales, using different shades and line thicknesses to create aesthetic variation. Previous Next Part of the beauty of generating art from code is that once the base program is written, modifications of this type (scaling, layering, etc.) are quick and easy. This is part of why the genre lends itself so well to experimentation, either manually or through randomisation. Finally, let’s add some colour. Shown below are a few more layered Truchet patterns, created with somewhat randomised sizes and scales. Previous Next The addition of colour not only makes the patterns much more interesting to look at, but differentiates them even further from each other, taking us further and further from the basic tiles we started with. The beauty and complexity of the final artwork disguises the simplicity of the building blocks - a statement that is true of the simple patterns seen in this post, but also, I think, of generative art as a whole.</summary></entry></feed>